<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc consensus="yes" ?>
<rfc 
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
  category="std"
  docName="draft-ietf-idr-fsv2-ip-basic-04"
  submissionType="IETF" 
  ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="BGP FSv2 Basic IP">BGP Flow Specification Version 2 - for Basic IP </title>
    <author fullname="Susan Hares" initials="S" surname="Hares">
      <organization>Hickory Hill Consulting</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>7453 Hickory Hill</street>
          <city>Saline</city>
          <region>MI</region>
          <code>48176</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1-734-604-0332</phone>
        <email>shares@ndzh.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Donald Eastlake" initials="D" surname="Eastlake">
      <organization>Independent</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>         
        <street>2386 Panoramic Circle</street>
          <city>Apopka</city>
          <region>FL</region>
          <code>32703</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1-508-333-2270</phone>
        <email>d3e3e3@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Jie Dong" initials="J" surname="Dong" >
      <organization> Huawei Technologies</organization>        
      <address>
        <postal>         
          <street>No. 156 Beiqing Road</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jie.dong@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author> 
    <author fullname="Chaitanya Yadlapalli" initials="C" surname="Yadlapalli">
      <organization>ATT</organization>        
      <address>
        <postal>         
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>cy098d@att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Sven Maduschke" initials="S" surname="Maduscke" >
      <organization> Verizon</organization>        
      <address>
        <postal>         
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>DE</country>
        </postal>
        <email>sven.maduschke@de.verizon.com</email>
      </address>
    </author> 
    <author fullname="Jeff Haas" initials="J" surname="Haas" >
      <organization> HPE</organization>        
      <address>
        <postal>         
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jeffrey.haas@hpe.com</email>
      </address>
    </author> 
    <date year="2026" />
    <area>Routing Area</area>
    <workgroup>IDR Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>RFC</keyword>
    <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>
    <keyword>I-D</keyword>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>BGP FSv2 - IP Basic</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>BGP flow specification version 1 (FSv1), defined in RFC 8955, RFC
      8956, and RFC 9117 describes the distribution of traffic filter policy
      (traffic filters and actions) distributed via BGP. During the deployment
      of BGP FSv1 a number of issues were detected, so version 2 of the BGP
      flow specification (FSv2) protocol addresses these issues.  In order to
      provide a clear demarcation between FSv1 and FSv2, a different NLRI
      encapsulates FSv2.</t>

      <t>The IDR WG requires two implementation. Early feedback on
      implementations of FSv2 indicate that FSv2 has a correct design
      direction, but that breaking FSv2 into a progression of documents would
      aid deployment of the draft (basic, adding more filters, and adding more
      actions). This document specifies the basic FSv2 NLRI with user ordering
      of filters added to FSv1 IP Filters and FSv2 actions.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Version 2 of BGP flow specification was original defined in 
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-v2"></xref> (BGP FSv2).</t>

      <t>FSv2 is an update to BGP Flow specification version 1 (BGP FSv1).  BGP
      FSv1 as defined in <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>, 
      <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>, and <xref target="RFC9117"></xref>
      specified 2 SAFIs (133, 134) to be used with IPv4 AFI (AFI = 1) and IPv6
      AFI (AFI=2).</t>

      <t>The initial BGP FSv2 specification had the correct direction, but it
      contained than the early implementers desired. The imoplmenters desired a
      progression of  documents with smaller incremental changes (basic FSv2,
      adding more filters, and adding more actions.)</t> 

      <t>This draft (FSv2 Basic) provides the basic FSv2 framework
      specification for transmitting user-ordered IP filters in the FSV2 NLRI
      and associating Flow Spec actions by transmitting the FLow Spec Extended
      Community(FS-EC) with the FSv2 NLRI.  If a filter match links to a single
      FS-EC action, the single action succeeds or fails. If a filte rmatch
      links to mutiple actions, there is a potential for interactions.  Section
      x.x discusses how to analyze the interaction by categories and solutions
      to issues with multiple FSv2-EC actions interacting. A complete solution
      requires the BGP Community Attribute see 
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-wide-bgp-communities"></xref>) with FSv2
      Container defined in the 
      <xref target="I-D.hares-idr-fsv2-more-ip-actions"></xref>.</t> 

      <t>This document defines 2 new SAFIs (TBD1, TBD2) for FSv2 to be used
      with 5 AFIs   (1, 2, 6, 25, and 31) to allow user-ordered lists of
      traffic match filters for user-ordered traffic match actions encoded in
      Extended Communities (FS-EC) or a newly defined BGP.  FSv2 does not
      require combinations of FSv2 AFI/SAFIs to be implemented (10
      combinations).  An implementation is required to implement only 1 these
      combinations to be compliant.  For example, a compliant implementation
      might only define the FSv2 NLRI for IPv4 for IP forwarding (AFI=1,
      SAFI=TBD1).</t>

      <t>FSv1 and FSv2 use different AFI/SAFIs to send flow specification
      filters.  Since BGP  route selection is performed per AFI/SAFI, this
      approach can be termed “ships in the night” based on AFI/SAFI.</t>

      <t>The remainder of section 1 provides background on why the FSv2 was
      necessary to fix problems with FSv1.  Section 2 contains a Primer on
      FSv2.  Section 3 contains the encoding rules for FSv2 and user-based
      encoding sent via BGP.  Section 4 describes how to validate and order
      FSv2 NLRI.  Sections 5-8 discusses scalability, optional security
      additions, security considerations, and IANA considerations.</t>          

      <section anchor="introFSv2" title="Why Flow Specification v2">
        <t>Modern IP routers have the capability to forward traffic and to
        classify, shape, rate limit, filter, or redirect packets based on
        administratively defined policies. These traffic policy mechanisms
        allow the operator to define match rules that operate on multiple
        fields within header of an IP data packet.  The traffic policy allows
        actions to be taken upon a match to be associated with each match rule.
        These rules can be more widely defined as “event-condition-action”
        (ECA) rules where the event is always the reception of a packet.</t>

        <t>BGP (<xref target="RFC4271"></xref>) flow specification as defined
        by <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>, <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>,
        <xref target="RFC9117"></xref> specifies the distribution of traffic
        filter policy (traffic filters and actions) via BGP to a mesh of BGP
        peers (IBGP and EBGP peers).  The traffic filter policy is applied when
        packets are received on a router with the flow specification function
        turned on. The flow specification protocol defined in
        <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>, <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>, and 
        <xref target="RFC9117"></xref> will be called BGP flow specification
        version 1 (BGP FSv1) in this draft.</t> 

        <t>Multiple deployed applications currently use BGP FSv1 to distribute
        traffic filter policy.  These applications include: 1) mitigation of
        Denial of Service (DoS), 2) traffic filtering in BGP/MPLS VPNS, and 3)
        centralized traffic control for networks utilizing SDN control of
        router firewall functions, 4) classifiers for insertion in an SFC, and
        5) filters for SRv6 (segment routing v6).</t>

        <t>During the deployment of BGP flow specification v1, the following
        issues were detected:

          <list style="symbols"> 
            <t>lack of a TLV encoding prevented extension of encodings (FSv1
            uses TV (type-value),</t>
            <t>inability to allow users to define order for filtering
            rules,</t>
            <t>inability to allow users to define order for multiple actions,
            and </t>
            <t>lack of clear rules for multiple actions per filter match that
            provide default actions on the order of actions and what happens
            when an action fails.</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>Networks currently cope with these issues above by constraining
        deployments or using topology/deployment specific workaround.</t>

        <t>FSv1 is a critical component of deployed applications. Therefore,
        this specification defines how FSv2 will interact with BGP peers that
        support either FSv2, FSv1, or FSv2 and FSv1. It is expected that a
        transition to FSv2 will occur over time as new applications require
        FSv2 features.</t>        
      </section> 
      <section title="Definitions and Acronyms">
        <t>
          <dl>
          <dt>AFI-</dt> <dd>Address Family Identifier</dd>
          <dt>AS -</dt> <dd>Autonomous System </dd>
          <dt>BGP Session ephemeral state -</dt><dd>state which does not survive the loss of BGP peer session.</dd>
          <dt>BGP Commmunity Path Attribute -</dt><dd>BGP Community Path attribute with a FS TLV defined by 
          <xref target="I-D.hares-idr-fsv2-more-ip-actions"></xref></dd> 
          <dt>Configuration state -</dt><dd>state which persist across a reboot of software module within 
          a routing system or a reboot of a hardware routing device.</dd>
          <dt>CPA -</dt><dd>BGP Community Path Attribute </dd>
          <dt>DDoS -</dt><dd>Distributed Denial of Service.</dd>
          <dt>Ephemeral state -</dt><dd>state which does not survive the reboot of a software module,
          or a hardware reboot. Ephemeral state can be ephemeral configuration state or 
          operational state.</dd> 
          <dt>FSv1 -</dt><dd>Flow Specification version 1 [RFC8955] [RFC8956] </dd>
          <dt>FSv2 -</dt><dd>Flow Specification version 2 (this document) </dd>
          <dt>FS -</dt><dd>Flow Specification (either v1 or v2) </dd> 
          <dt> FS-CPA -</dt><dd>Flow Specification Actions defined in Community Path Attribute </dd>
          <dt>FS-EC -</dt><dd>FS related Extended Community with FS actions </dd>
          <dt>FSv1-EC -</dt><dd>FSv1 Extended Community with FS Actions supported by FSv1 </dd>
          <dt>FSv2-EC -</dt><dd>FSv2 Extended Community with FS Actions supported by FSv2 </dd>
          <dt>NETCONF -</dt><dd>The Network Configuration Protocol <xref target="RFC6241"></xref>.</dd>
          <dt>RESTCONF -</dt><dd>The RESTCONF configurati on Protocol <xref target="RFC8040"></xref> </dd>
          <dt>RIB -</dt><dd>Routing Information Base.</dd>
          <dt>ROA -</dt><dd> Route Origin Authentication <xref target="RFC9582"></xref></dd>
          <dt>RR -</dt><dd>Route Reflector.</dd>
          <dt> SAFI –</dt><dd>Subsequent Address Family Identifier </dd>
          </dl>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="RFC 2119 language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref
        target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and only
        when, they appear in all capitals as shown here.</t>
      </section> 
    </section>

    <section title="Flow Specification Version 2 Primer ">
      <t> A BGP Flow Specification (v1 or v2) is an n-tuple containing one or
      more match criteria that can be applied to IP traffic, traffic
      encapsulated in IP traffic or traffic associated with IP traffic. The
      exact traffic match depends on the FSv2 AFI/SAFI.</t>

      <t> A given Flow Specification NLRI may be associated with a set of path
      attributes depending on the particular application, and these attributes
      within that set may or may not include reachability information (e.g.,
      NEXT_HOP).  The BGP path attributes associated with FSv2 may also contain
      Extended Community attributes <xref target="RFC4360"></xref> and Community
      Container Path attributes
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-wide-bgp-communities"></xref> with FSv2
      actions.</t>

      <t>BGP processing treats the NLRI as a key to entries in AFI/SAFI BGP
      databases. Entries that are placed in the Loc-RIB are then associated with
      a given set of semantics which are application dependent. Standard BGP 
      mechanisms such as update filtering by NLRI or by attributes such as AS_PATH or 
      large communities apply to the BGP Flow Specification defined NLRI-types.</t>

      <t>This FSv2 for basic IP forwarding specification only requires the use
      of Extended Communities to associate FS action with FSv2 filters found in
      FSv2 NLRI.</t>

      <t>The FSv2 features of multiple actions with user ordering of actions or
      dependencies between actions requires the BGP Community Attribute
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-wide-bgp-communities"></xref> with a FSv2
      Component as defined in <xref target="I-D.hares-idr-fsv2-more-ip-actions"></xref>.</t>

      <t> Network operators can control the propagation of BGP routes by
      enabling or disabling the exchange of routes for a particular AFI/SAFI
      pair on a particular peering session.  As such, the Flow Specification may
      be distributed to only a portion of the BGP infrastructure.</t>

      <section title="Flow Specification v1 (FSv1) SAFIs ">
        <t>The FSv1 NLRI defined in <xref target="RFC8955"></xref> and
        <xref target="RFC8956"></xref> include 13 match conditions encoded for
        the following AFI/SAFIs:

        <list style="symbol">
          <t>IPv4 traffic: AFI:1, SAFI:133 </t>
          <t>IPv6 Traffic: AFI:2,  SAFI:133 </t>
          <t>BGP/MPLS IPv4 VPN: AFI:1, SAFI: 134 </t>
          <t>BGP/MPLS IPv6 VPN: AFI:2, SAFI: 134</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>Match conditions are ordered by component type in ascending order.
        If multiple component types filters exist, the ordering within a
        component type is defined by the component type.  The FSv1 component
        format does not provide enough information to create a unique
        canonically sorted list for all implementations in all deployments.</t>          

        <t>The actions standardized for in <xref target="RFC8955"></xref> and
        <xref target="RFC8956"></xref> are: 

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>accept packet (default),</t>
          <t>traffic flow limitation by bytes (0x6), </t>
          <t>traffic-action (0x7),</t>
          <t>redirect traffic to VPN (0x8),</t>
          <t>mark traffic (0x9), and </t>
          <t>traffic flow rate limiting (12, 0xC)</t>
        </list> 
        </t>

        <t>An SFC action <xref target="RFC9015"></xref> defines a redirection
        of a data flow to an entry point into a specific SFP (Service Function
        Path) </t> <t>While IDR has proposed other Extended Community Actions,
        no additional actions have completed the standardization process.</t>

        <t>Additional proposals for FS Actions in Extended Communities exist,
        but these are still in the standardization process.  As such, these new
        FS actions will fall under FSv2 rules for Extended Communities.</t>         

      </section>
      <section title="Transition to FSv2">
        <t>This specification specification defines AFI/SAFI pairs to support
        Flow Spec for IPv4 IP  IPv6, L2, IPv4 VPNs, IPv6 VPNs, L2VPN, SFC, and
        SFC VPN supports the components and actions for the following: 

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>IPv4 (AFI=1, SAFI=TBD1),</t>
          <t>IPv6 (AFI=2, SAFI=TBD1),</t>
          <t>L2 (AFI=6, SAFI=TDB1) [described in [I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-l2vpn]),</t>
          <t>BGP/MPLS IPv4 VPN: (AFI=1, SAFI=TBD2),</t>
          <t>BGP/MPLS IPv6 VPN: (AFI=2, SAFI=TBD2),</t>
          <t>BGP/MPLS L2VPN (AFI=25, SAFI=TDB2) [described in [I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-l2vpn]),</t>
          <t>SFC: (AFI=31, SAFI=TBD1),</t>
          <t>SFC VPN (AFI=31, SAFI=TBD2),</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>One question asked by developers is what AFI/SAFI is required for
        FSv2 IP Basic compliance.  BGP negotiates support for each AFI/SAFI, so
        FSv2 IP Basic support for non-VPN could be as little as FSv2 for IPv4
        forwarding (AFI/SAFI: 1/TBD1),</t>

        <t>The IDR specification for L2 VPN traffic was specified in 
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-l2vpn"></xref>.  An IDR
        specification for tunneled traffic is in
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-nvo3"></xref>.  
        Both of these drafts were targeted for FSv1, but the WG decided to
        require these to FSv2 TLV formats.</t>
      </section> 

      <section title="FSv2 Overview">
        <t>FSv2 allows the user to order the flow specification rules and the
        actions associated with a rule. Each FSv2 rule may have one or more
        match conditions and one or more associated actions.</t>

        <t>FSv2 operates in the ships-in-the night model with FSv1 so network
        operators can manipulate which the distribution of FSv2 and FSv1 using
        configuration parameters.</t>

        <t>An FSv2 peer may receive BGP NLRI routes from a FSv1 peer or a BGP
        peer that does not support FSv1 or FSv2.  The capabilities sent by a
        remote BGP peer indicate what FS supported by the AFI/SAFI (FSv1 NLRI
        or FSv2 NLRI or none).</t>

        <t>The basic principles regarding ordering of flow specification
        filter rules are: 
          <list>
            <t>1) Rule-0 (zero) is defined to be 0/0 with the “permit-all” action.</t>
            <t>2) FSv2 filter rules are ordered based on user-specified order. 

              <list>
                <t>The user-specified order is carried in the FSv2 NLRI and a
                numerical lower value takes precedence over a numerically
                higher value.  For rules received with the same order value,
                the filter rules are ordered by FSv2 component number and then
                by rules specified by the component.</t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>3) Importing FSv1 into a combined FSv2 and FSv2 rule set
            requires starting FSv2 with Rule 1 and adding FSv1 rules are added
            after FSv2 rules.

              <list>
                <t>For example, BGP Peer A has FSv2 data base with 10 FSv2
                rules (1-10). Suppose that, FSv1 user ordered FS are configured
                to start at 301 so 10 FSv1 rules are added at 301-310.</t>
              </list>  
            </t>
            <t>4) One or more action can be linked to a filter rule 

              <list>
                <t>If a single action is linked, the action either succeeds or
                fails.</t> 
                <t>if multiple actions are linked to a filter rule via FSv2
                Extended Communities, the implementation MUST follow the
                FSv2-EC interaction rules in section x.x or have a local
                configuration knob to indicate local interaction rules.
                Implementations within a network SHOULD follow the same
                interaction rules</t>

                <t>If an implementation allows for FSv2 actions with
                user-ordering and Extended Community actions, the by default
                the Extended Community are ordered after the user-ordered
                actions.</t>    
              </list> 
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t> Figure 1 shows a diagram of the FSv2 
          logical data structures with 5 rules 
          for IP Basic functionality.             
          <figure>
          <artwork>
     
         +--------------------------------------+
         | Flow Specification (FS)              | 
         |  Policy                              | 
         +--------------------------------------+        
                    ^               ^              ^
             |               |              | 
             |               |              |   
    +--------^----+  +-------^-------+     +-------------+    
    |   FS Rule 1 |  |   FS Rule 2   | ... |  FS rule 5  |
    +-------------+  +---------------+     +-------------+
                          :  :  :  :               
        :.................:  :  :  :           
        :            :............:  :  :         
     +--V--+ +--V-------+       :  :              
     |order| |Dependent | ......:  :..       
     |     | | filter   | :          :
     +-----+ | chain    | :          :
             +----------+ :          :
                          :          :        
                          :          :        
                     .....:          :........   
                     :                     :
           +---------V-----------+    +----V-------------+
           |  Rule Condition     |    |   Rule Action    |
           |  in BGP NLRIs       |    | in BGP extended  |
           | AFI/SAFI 1/133,     |    | Communities      |
           | 1/134, 2/133, 2/134 |    |                  |  
           +-------------------+      +------------------+
               :     :    :                 :      :    :
          .....:     .    :.....       .....:      .    :.....
          :          :         :       :           :         :
     +----V---+  +---V----+ +--V---+ +-V------+ +--V-----++--V---+
     |  Match |  | match  | |match | | Action | | action ||action|
     |Operator|  |Variable| |Value | |Operator| |variable|| Value|
     |*1      |  |        | |      | |(subtype| |        ||      |
     +--------+  +--------+ +------+ +--------+ +--------++------+
     
       *1 match operator may be complex. 
     
       Figure 2-1: BGP Flow Specification v1 Policy 
          </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section> 

    <section title="FSv2 NLRI Formats and Actions">
      <section title="FSv2 NLRI Format">
        <t> The BGP FSv2 supports NRLI with the format for AFIs for IPv4 (AFI =
        1), IPv6 (AFI = 2), L2 (AFI = 6), L2VPN (AFI=25), and SFC (AFI=31) with
        SAFIs TBD1 (Flow Spec) and TBD2 (Flow Spec for VPNs) to support
        transmission of the flow specification which supports user ordering of
        traffic filters and actions for IP traffic and IP VPN traffic.</t>

        <t>A compliant FSv2 implementation only has to implement one AFI/SAFI
        pair out of the full list of NRLIs.  For example, a compliant FSv2
        implementation could only implement IPv4 FSv2 (AFI=1, SAFI=TBD1).</t>

        <t>This NLRI information is encoded using MP_REACH_NLRI and
        MP_UNREACH_NLRI attributes defined in <xref target="RFC4760"></xref>.
        When advertising FSv2 NLRI, the length of the Next-Hop Network Address
        MUST be set to 0. Upon reception, the Network Address in the Next-Hop
        field MUST be ignored.</t>

        <t>Implementations wishing to exchange flow specification rules MUST
        use BGP's Capability Advertisement facility to exchange the
        Multiprotocol Extension Capability Code (Code 1) as defined in <xref
        target="RFC4760"></xref>, and indicate a capability for FSv1, FSv2
        (Code TBD3), or both.</t> 

        <t>The AFI/SAFI NLRI for BGP Flow Specification version 2 (FSv2) has the format:
         <figure>
         <artwork>
     +--------------------------------+
     | NLRI length (2 octets)         |
     +--------------------------------+
     | TLVs+                          |
     +--------------------------------+
     
      Figure 3-1 - NLRI format 
          </artwork>
          </figure> 
        </t>

        <t>where:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>NLRI length: length of field including all SubTLVs in octets.</t> 
            <t>TLV+ - indicates the repetition of the TLV field</t>
          </list> 
        </t> 
        <t>Each each TLV has the Format:
          <figure>
          <artwork>
      
         TLV format   
     +--------------------------------+
     | +============================+ |
     | | order (4 octets)           | |
     | +----------------------------+ |
     | | Dependent filters chain    | | 
     | |(type, chain ID, count,     | |
     | | item) (8 octets)           | |
     | +----------------------------+ | 
     | + FSv2 Filter type (2 octet) + |
     | +----------------------------+ |
     | + length TLVs (2 octet)      + |
     | + ---------------------------+ |
     | + value (variable)           + |
     | +----------------------------+ |
     +-------------------------------+

     Figure 3-2 - TLV format within FSv2 NLRI  
          </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>

        <t>where:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t>order: flow-specification global rule order number (4 octets).</t>
            <t> Dependent Filters Chain: 8 octets for identifying a chain of
            FSv2 filters that must be deployed at the same time.  

              <list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="Why needed in FSv2:">Flow specification filters
                distributed in BGP UPDATE packets may be broken into multiple
                packets. In FSv2, the dependent filter ID allows the filter
                chains to be identified across all user-defined or default
                filters.  The rules can be installed from BGP into the firewall
                after all filters have been installed.</t>
 
                <t hangText="For basic FSV2:">This field is required to be set
                to all zero, and ignored upon reception.</t>

                <t hangText="For future FSV2:">Future specifications will
                specify the use of this field, and future specifications will
                continue to ignore the field if the value is all zeros.</t>
              </list> 
            </t>

            <t>FSv2 Filter type: contains a type for FSv2 TLV format of the
            NRLI (2 octets).  This type specifies support for a set of
            components.  [Editor's note: We need to decide between Option 2 or
            Option 1.  Option 2 makes provides a better default ordering for
            frame/packet filters.

              <list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="Option 1"> ascending order (draft-ietf-idr-fsv2-ip-basic-02)

                  <list>
                    <t>0 - reserved, </t>
                    <t>1 - IP Basic Filter rules </t>
                    <t>2 - IP Extended Filter Rules </t>
                    <t>3 - MPLS Filter Rules </t>
                    <t>4 - L2 traffic rules</t>
                    <t>5 - SFC Traffic rules </t>
                    <t>6 - Tunneled traffic </t> 
                  </list>
                </t>
                <t hangText="Option 2"> ordering by frame/packet (new) 
                  <list>
                    <t>0 - reserved, </t>
                    <t>50 -  L2 Traffic fules  </t>
                    <t>100 - MPLS traffic rules</t>
                    <t>150 - SFC Traffic rules </t>
                    <t>200 - Tunneled traffic </t> 
                    <t>256 - IP Basic Filter Rules (bit 1 of high bit) </t>
                    <t>280 - IP Extended Filter Rules </t> 
                  </list>
                </t> 
              </list> 
            </t> 

            <t>length-TLV: is the length of the value part of the Sub-TLV,</t>
            <t>value: value depends on the type of FSv2 Filter type.</t>
          </list>  
        </t>

        <t>FSv2 implementations MUST pass valid filter TLVs even if the
        implementation does not support these installation of these a particular
        type of filter rules.</t>

        <t>This specification only defines operation of the IP Basic Filter Rules
        that all FSv2 must support.  </t> 

        <section title="Ordering of TLVs within the FSv2 NLRI">
          <t> For ease of processing, the ordering within the FSv2 NLRI MUST be
          by order number.  Within an order value (e.g. 20), the filters MUST
          group the filters by the same filter type (e.g. IP Basic filter rules),
          and order the groups of filters by filter type (ascending values).</t>

          <t>The order within a filter type (e.g. IP Basic Filters) MUST be by
          the component type. If multiple components of the same type exist, the
          component ordering is specified by the component definition (as in
          FSv1).</t>
        </section> 

        <section title="Partial Deployments">
          <t>Partial deployments can occur for two reasons: 
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Only a portion of the nodes in a network with FSv2 support
              installing new FSv2 Filter types with new FSv2 components. Other
              nodes (such as RRs), check the syntax, but do not handle the
              semantic meaning.</t>

              <t>During upgrades, a portion of the nodes know about a new Filter
              type with the components, but other nodes do not.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>Editor: Are there others? </t> 
        </section> 
      </section>

      <section title="FSv2 Basic IP Filters " >
        <section title="Operators for comparison">
          <section title="Numeric Operator (numeric_op)">
            <t>This operator is encoded as shown in Figure 3-3. 
              <figure>
              <artwork>

          0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
        +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
        | e | a |  len  | 0 |lt |gt |eq |
        +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+

              Figure 3-3: Numeric Operator (numeric_op)

              </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>

            <dl>
              <dt>e (end-of-list bit): </dt>
              <dd>Set in the last {op, value} pair in the list</dd>

              <dt>a (AND bit):</dt>
              <dd> If unset, the result of the previous {op, value} pair is
              logically ORed with the current one.  If set, the operation is a
              logical AND.  In the first operator octet of a sequence, it MUST be
              encoded as unset and MUST be treated as always unset on decoding.
              The AND operator has higher priority than OR for the purposes of
              evaluating logical expressions.</dd>

              <dt>len (length): </dt>
              <dd>The length of the value field for this operator given as (1
              &lt;&lt; len).  This encodes 1 (len=00), 2 (len=01), 4 (len=10), and
              8 (len=11) octets.</dd>

              <dt>0</dt>
              <dd>MUST be set to 0 on NLRI encoding and MUST be ignored during decoding</dd>        

              <dt>lt</dt>
              <dd>less-than comparison between data and value</dd>

              <dt>gt:</dt>
              <dd>greater-than comparison between data and value</dd>

              <dt>eq:</dt>
              <dd>equality between data and value</dd>
            </dl>

            <t> The bits lt, gt, and eq can be combined to produce common
            relational operators, such as "less or equal", "greater or equal", and
            "not equal to", as shown in Table 3-1.</t>

            <t> 
              <figure> 
              <artwork> 

                  +====+====+====+==================================+
                  | lt | gt | eq | Resulting operation              |
                  +====+====+====+==================================+
                  | 0  | 0  | 0  | false (independent of the value) |
                  +----+----+----+----------------------------------+
                  | 0  | 0  | 1  | == (equal)                       |
                  +----+----+----+----------------------------------+
                  | 0  | 1  | 0  | &gt; (greater than)                 |
                  +----+----+----+----------------------------------+
                  | 0  | 1  | 1  | &lt;= (greater than or equal)       |
                  +----+----+----+----------------------------------+
                  | 1  | 0  | 0  | &lt; (less than)                    |
                  +----+----+----+----------------------------------+
                  | 1  | 0  | 1  | &lt;= (less than or equal)          |
                  +----+----+----+----------------------------------+
                  | 1  | 1  | 0  | != (not equal value)             |
                  +----+----+----+----------------------------------+
                  | 1  | 1  | 1  | true (independent of the value)  |
                  +----+----+----+----------------------------------+

                     Table 3-1: Comparison Operation Combinations
              </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
          </section> 

          <section title="Bitmask Operator (bitmask_op)">
            <t>This operator is encoded as shown in Figure 3-4. 
              <figure>
              <artwork>

           0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
          +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
          | e | a |  len  | 0 | 0 |not| m |
          +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+

          Figure 3-4 Bitmask Operator (bitmask_op)
            </artwork>
            </figure> 

            Where:</t>

            <dl>
              <dt>e, a, len (end-of-list bit, AND bit, and length field):</dt>
              <dd>Most significant nibble; defined in the Numeric Operator format
              in section 3-x.</dd>

              <dt>not (NOT bit):</dt>
              <dd>If set, logical negation of operation.</dd>

              <dt>m (Match bit):</dt>
              <dd>If set, this is a bitwise match operation defined as
              "(data AND value) == value"; if unset, (data AND value) evaluates to
              TRUE if any of the bits in the value mask are set in the data.</dd>

              <dt>0 (all 0 bits):</dt>
              <dd> MUST be set to 0 on NLRI encoding and MUST be ignored during
              decoding</dd>

            </dl>
          </section> 
        </section> 

        <section title="IP Basic Filters (Filter type=TBD )">
          <t>The format of the IP Basic TLV value field is shown in Figure 3-5.
          The IP header for the VPN case is specified in section 3.5.</t>

          <t>
            <figure>
            <artwork>

         Top-level TLV            
       +-------------------------------+   
       | +============================+ |
       | | order (4 octets)           | |
       | +----------------------------+ |
       | | dependency filter chain    | |
       | |  (8 octets)                | |
       | +----------------------------+ | 
       | + FSv2 Filter type (2 octets)| |
       | | option1: 1, option2: 256   | | 
       | +----------------------------+ |
       | + length (2 octet)           + |
       | + ---------------------------+ |
       | + value (variable)           + |
       | +----------------------------+ |
       +--------------------------------+

      Figure 3-5 NLRI format for FSv2 IP Filter Type
            </artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>

          <t>Where: 
            <list> 
              <t>order - is an 4 octet field with a value 1-N.  The value 0 (zero)
              is invalid, and the TLV should be "treated-as-withdrawl".</t>

              <t>dependency filter chain - is an 8 octet field which must be all
              zero for the IP Basic Filter rules.</t> 

              <t>length - is a 2 octet field indicating the length of the value
              field.</t>

              <t>value - is a variable field comprised of a sequence of component TLVs: 
                <figure>
                <artwork>

       +--------------------------------+
       | + ---------------------------+ |
       | + Components TLV+ (variable) + |
       | +----------------------------+ |
       +--------------------------------+
       
       Figure 3-6 Value Field 
                </artwork> 
                </figure>
              </t>

              <t>
                <figure> 
                <artwork> 

        Where the Component TLVs are: 

         +----------------------------+
         |  Component Type (1 octet)  |
         +----------------------------+
         |  length (1 octet)          |
         + ---------------------------+
         |  value (variable)          |
         +----------------------------+
         
      Figure 3-7 – IP header Component TLVs  

                </artwork>
                </figure>
              </t>

              <t>Where:
                <list>
                  <t>Component type: component values are defined in the “Flow
                  Specification Component types” registry for IPv4 and IPv6 by
                  <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>, <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>,
                  and <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-srv6"></xref></t>

                  <t>length: length of SubTLV (varies depending on the component
                  type).  If the length of the component types does match the valid
                  defined length(s) for the component, the component type is
                  ignored and the Filter type TLV is "treated-as-withdrawl".</t>

                  <t>value: dependent on component type.</t>
                </list>
              </t>

              <t>Many of the components use the operators [numeric_op] and
              [bitmask_op] defined in <xref target="RFC8955"></xref></t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>The list of valid SubTLV types appears in Table 3-2 for filter type of
          IP Filters (type=1).  Other filters beyond these filters may be defined
          other filter types (e.g. IP Extended Filters).</t>

          <t>
            <figure> 
            <artwork>
      Table 3-2 FSv2 IP Basic TLV Components 
                        
      Sub-TLV   Definition 
      --------  ---------------------  
         0 -    Reserved 
         1 -    IP Destination prefix 
         2 -    IP Source prefix 
         3 –    IPv4 Protocol / 
                IPv6 Upper Layer Protocol
         4 –    Port  
         5 –    Destination Port 
         6 –    Source Port
         7 –    ICMPv4 type / ICMPv6 type  
         8 –    ICMPv4 code / ICPv6 code 
         9 –    TCP Flags 
        10 –    Packet length
        11 –    DSCP  
        12 –    Fragment 
        13 –    Flow Label 
        14-255  Reserved 
       
            </artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Ordering within the IP Basic Filter TLVs">
          <t> The ordering of components within the value field of the IP Basic TLV
          follows the FSv1 rules.  The following is a restatement of FSv1 rules in
          FSv2 terms.</t>

          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>1) order by component types (1-13).</t>

              <t>(2) If the components are the same, then the value fields are
              compared using mechanisms defined in <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>
              and <xref target="RFC8956"></xref> and MUST be in ascending order.
              NLRIs having component TLVs which do not follow the above ordering
              rules MUST be considered as malformed by a BGP FSv2 propagator. This
              rule prevents any ambiguities that arise from the multiple copies of
              the same NLRI from multiple BGP FSv2 propagators.  A BGP
              implementation SHOULD treat such malformed NLRIs as
              "treat-as-withdrawl".  <xref target="RFC7606"></xref>.</t>
            </list> 
          </t>

          <t>See <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>, <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>,
          and for details on per component ordering.</t>
        </section> 

        <section title="FSv2 Components for IP Basic TLVs">
          <section title="IP Destination Prefix (type = 1)">
            <t>IPv4 Name: IP Destination Prefix   (reference: <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>)</t>
            <t>IPv6 Name: IPv6 Destination Prefix (reference: <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>)</t>
            <t></t>
            <t>IPv4 length: Prefix length in bits</t>
            <t>IPv4 value: IPv4 Prefix (variable length)</t>
            <t>IPv6 length: length of value</t>
            <t>IPv6 value: [offset (1 octet)] [pattern (variable)] [padding(variable)]</t>
            <t>If IPv6 length = 0 and offset = 0, then component matches every
            address.  Otherwise, length must be offset "less than" length "less
            than" 129 or component is malformed.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="IP Source Prefix (type = 2) ">
            <t>IPv4 Name: IP Source Prefix    (reference: <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>) </t>
            <t>IPv6 Name: IPv6 Source Prefix  (reference: <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>) </t>
            <t></t>
            <t>IPv4 length: Prefix length in bits</t>
            <t>IPv4 value: Source IPv4 Prefix (variable length)</t>
            <t>IPv6 length: length of value</t>
            <t>IPv6 value: [offset (1 octet)] [pattern (variable)][padding(variable)]</t>
            <t></t>
            <t>If IPv6 length = 0 and offset = 0, then component matches every
            address.  Otherwise, length must be offset &lt; length &lt; 129 or
            component is malformed.</t>
          </section>
          <section title="IP Protocol (type = 3) ">
            <t>IPv4 Name: IP Protocol  IP Source Prefix  (reference: <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>)</t>
            <t>IPv6 Name: IPv6 Upper-Layer Protocol:   (reference: <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>)</t>
            <t></t>
            <t>IPv4 length: variable</t>
            <t>IPv4 value: [numeric_op, value]+</t>
            <t></t>
            <t>IPv6 length: variable</t>
            <t>IPv6 value: [numeric_op, value]+</t>
            <t>where the value following each numeric_op is a single octet.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Port (type = 4)">
            <t>IPv4/IPv6 Name: Port (reference:  <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>),
            <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>)</t>
            <t>Filter defines: a set of port values to match either destination
            port or source port.</t>
            <t></t>
            <t>IPv4 length: variable</t>
            <t>IPv4 value: [numeric_op, value]+</t>
            <t></t>
            <t>IPv6 length: variable</t>
            <t>IPv6 value: [numeric_op, value]+</t>
            <t></t>
            <t>where the value following each numeric_op is a single octet. </t>
            <t>Note-1: (from FSV1) In the presence of the port component
            (destination or source port), only a TCP (port 6) or UDP (port 17)
            packet can match the entire flow specification.  If the packet is
            fragmented and this is not the first fragment, then the system may not
            be able to find the header.  At this point, the FSv2 filter may fail to
            detect the correct flow.  Similarly, if other IP options or the
            encapsulating security payload (ESP) is present, then the  node may not
            be able to describe the transport header and the FSv2 filter may fail
            to detect the flow.</t>
            <t>The restriction in note-1 comes from the inheritance of the FSv1
            filter component for port.  If better resolution is desired, a new FSv2
            filter should be defined.</t>
            <t>Note-2: FSv2 component only matches the first upper layer protocol
            value.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Destination Port (type = 5) ">
            <t>IPv4/IPv6 Name: Destination Port    (reference:  <xref
            target="RFC8955"></xref>), <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>) </t>
            <t>Filter defines: a list of match filters for destination port for TCP
            or UDP within a received packet</t>
            <t>Length: variable</t>
            <t> Component Value format: [numeric_op, value]+</t>
          </section>
          <section title="Source Port (type = 6)  ">
            <t>IPv4/IPv6 Name: Source Port (reference:  <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>), <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>)</t>
            <t>Filter defines: a list of match filters for source port for TCP or UDP within a received packet</t>
            <t>IPv4/IPv6 length: variable</t>
            <t>IPv4/Ipv6 value: [numeric_op, value]+</t>
          </section>

          <section title="ICMP Type (type = 7) ">
            <t>IPv4: ICMP Type (reference:  <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>)</t>
            <t>Filter defines: Defines: a list of match criteria for ICMPv4 type</t>  
            <t>IPv6: ICMPv6 Type (reference: <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>) </t>
            <t>Filter defines: a list of match criteria for ICMPv6 type.</t>
            <t></t>
            <t>IPv4/IPv6 length: variable</t>
            <t>IPv4/IPv6 value: [numeric_op, value]+</t>
          </section>

          <section title="ICMP Code (type = 8) ">
            <t>IPv4: ICMP Type (reference:  <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>)</t>
            <t>Filter defines: a list of match criteria for ICMPv4 code.</t>  
            <t>IPv6: ICMPv6 Type (reference: <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>)</t>
            <t>Filter defines: a list of match criteria for ICMPv6 code.</t>
            <t></t>
            <t>IPv4/IPv6 length: variable</t>
            <t>IPv4/IPv6 value: [numeric_op, value]+ </t>
          </section>

          <section title="TCP Flags (type = 9) " >
            <t>IPv4/IPv6: TCP Flags Code  (reference:  <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>)</t>
            <t>Filter defines: a list of match criteria for TCP Control bits</t>  
            <t></t>
            <t>IPv4/IPv6 length: variable</t>
            <t>IPv4/IPv6 value: [bitmask_op, value]+</t>
            <t></t>
            <t>Note: a 2 octets bitmask match is always used for TCP-Flags </t> 
          </section>

          <section title="Packet length (type = 10 (0x0A)) ">
            <t>IPv4/IPv6: Packet Length (reference: <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>,
            <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>)</t>
            <t>Filter defines: a list of match criteria for length of packet
            (excluding L2 header but including IP header).</t>  
            <t>IPv4/IPv6 length: variable</t>
            <t>IPv4/IPv6 value: [numeric_op, value]+</t>
            <t></t>
            <t>Note:<xref target="RFC8955"></xref> uses either 1 or 2 octet values.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="DSCP (Differentiaed Services Code Point)(type = 11 (0x0B)) ">
            <t>IPv4/IPv6: DSCP Code  (reference:  <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>,
            <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>)</t>
            <t>Filter defines: a list of match criteria for DSCP code values to
            match the 6-bit DSCP field.</t> 
            <t></t>
            <t>IPv4/IPv6 length: variable</t>
            <t>IPv4/IPv6 value: [numeric_op, value]+</t>
            <t></t>
            <t>Note: This component uses the Numeric Operator (numeric_op)
            described in <xref target="RFC8955"></xref> in section 4.2.1.1.  Type
            11 component values MUST be encoded as single octet (numeric_op
            len=00).</t>
            <t>The six least significant bits contain the DSCP value.  All other
            bits SHOULD be treated as 0.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Fragment (type = 12 (0x0C))   ">
            <t>IPv4/IPv6: Fragment  (reference:  <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>,
            <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>)</t>
            <t>Filter defines: a list of match criteria for specific IP fragments.</t> 
            <t></t>
            <t>Length: variable</t>
            <t>Component Value format: [bitmask_op, value]+</t>
            <t>Bitmask values are:</t>
            <t>
              <figure>
              <artwork>
            0    1   2   3   4   5   6  7        
          +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+ 
          | 0 | 0 | 0 | 0 |LF |FF |IsF| DF| 
          +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+ 
                       Figure 3-8
              </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>

            <t>Where:
              <list>
                <t>DF (don’t fragment): match If IP header flags bit 1 (DF) is 1.</t>

                <t>IsF(is a fragment other than first: match if IP header fragment
                offset is not 0.</t>

                <t> FF (First Fragment): Match if <xref target="RFC0791"></xref>
                IP Header Fragment offset is zero and Flags Bit-2 (MF) is 1.</t>

                <t>LF (last Fragment): Match if <xref target="RFC0791"></xref> IP
                header Fragment is not 0 And Flags bit-2 (MF) is 0</t>

                <t>0: MUST be sent in NLRI encoding as 0, and MUST be ignored
                during reception.</t>
              </list>
            </t>
          </section>

          <section title="Flow Label(type = 13 (0xOD)) ">
            <t>IPv4/IPv6: Fragment  (reference:  <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>)</t>
            <t>Filter defines: a list of match criteria for 20-bit Flow Label in the IPv6 header field.</t> 
            <t></t>
            <t>Length: variable</t>
            <t>Component Value format: [numeric_op, value]+</t>
          </section> 
        </section> 
      </section>

      <section title="FSv2 Actions for FSv2 IP Basic ">
        <t> The IP Basic FSv2 allows FS actions to be sent in an Extended
        Community (FSv2-EC) for IPv4 and IPv6.   The Extended Community encodes
        the Flow Specification actions in the Extended IPv4 Community format
        <xref target="RFC4360"></xref> or in the extended IPv6 Community format
        <xref target="RFC5701"></xref>.</t>

        <t> A Flow Spec filter match maybe linked to only one Flow Spec action.
        For these deplyments, the details on multiple actions per flow spec
        filter match in this section can be ignored.</t>

        <t> When an operator defines multiple Flow Spec Extended Community
        (FS-EC) Actions for single filter match, it is possible that some FS-EC
        actions can interact If one sorts the FS-EC actions into categories,
        the interactions can be minimized. One example of such interactions is
        if the flow is redirect to a VRF and to a VPN. Another way two actions
        interact is if an action fails.  For example, if set DSCP action fails
        prior to redirect to a VPN may have undesired data flow patterns.</t>

        <t> This section defines the FS-EC actions, categories of FS-EC
        actions, and ways to minimize interactions between FS-EC actions.
        Section 3.3.1 describes the existing FS-EC action formats.  Section
        3.3.2 describes the interaction between FS-EC action, and categories of
        actions, and the way to minimizes interactions.  Should the BGP to
        distribute information about the configured interactions for sequences
        of multiple actions, Section 3.3 defines an optional FS-EC to pass
        information ordering of categories (user/this standard) and failure
        action (stop or best effort).</t> 

        <t>Note that FSv2 implementations that only associate 1 FSv2-EC per
        filter match do not need the FSv2-EC.</t> 

        <section title="FSv2 Extended Community Actions"> 
          <t>The FSv2 IP Basic uses FSv1 actions and defines for one one
          additional optional FSv2 specific FS-EC. This one optional action is
          the Action Chain Ordering (ACO) Extended Community (ACO-EC) which can
          pass around defaults currently only available by configuration in
          FSv1.</t>

          <section title="FSv2 Actions in Extended Community for IPv4">
            <t> The format of the Extended Community for IPv4 defined in <xref
            target="RFC4360"></xref> is shown in Figure 3-9 with 2 octet type
            that is split into a high byte and low byte.  The format of the
            IPv4 Extended Community is shown in Figure 3-10.  

              <figure>
              <artwork>

      0                   1                   2                   3
      0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |  Type high    |  Type low(*)  |                               |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+          Value (6 octets)     |
     |                                                               |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

                        Figure 3-9
              </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
            <t>
              <figure>
              <artwork>
     
                   Table 3-3 
      FSv1 Transitive Extended Communities for IP Basic 
          High-Low byte of Transitive FS-EC 
     
    H-L      FSv1 Description               Short-ID FS document
    ======   ==================             ======== ==========        
    0x01-0C  Transitive IPv4                RDIPv4   RDIP   
    0x07-02  FSv1 for an Interface set      TAIS     ifset                       
    0x09-xx  Redirect to Indirection ID     RGID     RGID  
    0x0b-00  SFC Reserved                   SFC-R    RFC9015 
    0x0b-01  SFVC SFIR POOL Identifier      SFIR-PI  RFC9015 
    0x0b-02  SFC MPLS label stack Swapping  SFC-MPLS RFC9015 
             or stacking labels
    0x80-06  Traffic rate limit by bytes    TRB      RFC8955
    0x80-07  Traffic Action                 TA       RFC8955
             (sample, terminal)   
    0x80-08  Redirection to VRF (2 AS form) RDIP     RFC8955
    0x80-09  Traffic mark DSCP              TM       RFC8955
    0x80-0C  Traffic rate limit by packets  TRP      RFC8955 
    0x81-08  Redirect to VPN (IPv4 form)    RDIP     RFC8955
    0x81-08  Redirect to VPN (4 AS form)    RDIP     RFC8955  
              </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>

            <t> Note the Short ID is simply a quick way for this document to
            reference a particular action.</t>

            <t>References: 
              <dl>
                <dt>ifset:</dt>
                <dd><xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-interfaceset"></xref></dd>

                <dt>RDIP:</dt>
                <dd><xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-redirect-ip"></xref></dd>

                <dt>RGID:</dt>
                <dd><xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-path-redirect"></xref></dd>

                <dt>RFC9015:</dt>
                <dd><xref target="RFC9015"></xref></dd>

                <dt>RFC8955:</dt>
                <dd><xref target="RFC8955"></xref></dd>
              </dl>
            </t>
          </section> 
          <section title="Flow Specification Actions in IPv6 forms">
            <t> The Transitive IPv6-Address-Specific Extended Community encodes
            the Flow Specification actions in the Extended Community format
            specified in <xref target="RFC5701"></xref> shown in Figure 3-10.
            Table 3-3 lists the 4 octet format for high-byte and low-byte.
            Note that there are two allocations for redirect from IPv6. 

              <figure>
              <artwork>

      0                   1                   2                   3
      0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     | Type (high)   |  Sub-type     |   Global Administrator        |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-|
     |         Global Administrator (cont.)                          |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |         Global Administrator (cont.)                          |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |         Global Administrator (cont.)                          |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     | Global Administrator (cont.)  |   Local Administrator         |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

                  Figure 3-10  
     
    The 20 octets of value are given in the following format: 
    Global Administrator: IPv6 address assigned by Internet Registry 
    Local Administrator:  2 bytes of Local Administrator 
              </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
            <t>
              <figure>
              <artwork>
                      Table 3-4
    Transitive IPv6-Address-Specific Extended Community Types 
     
    H-L byte  FSv1 Description        Short-ID FS document
    ======    ==================      ======== ==========
    0x0000    Unassigned 
    0x0001    Unassigned 
    0x0002    Route Target            RT        No
    0x0003    Route origin            ROrg      No (deprecated) 
    0x0004    OSPFv3 Route Attribute  OSPFv3    No (deprecated) 
    0x0005    FIT Tail Community      IFITv6    No 
    0x0006    Link Bandwidth          LBW       No        
    0x0008    Unassigned                    
    0x0009    Unassigned 
    0x000A    Unassigned  
    0x000B    VRF Route Import        VRP-I     No
    0x000C    FS Redirect to IPv6     RDIPv6C   Yes: RDIP
    0x000D    FS Redirect to IPv6     RDIPv6    Yes: RFC8956 
    0x000E    Unassigned 
    Ox000F    Unassigned 
    0x0010    Cisco VPN distinguisher Cisco-VPN  No 
    0x0011    UUID-based Route Target UUID-RT    No
    0x0012    Inter-ARea P2MP S-NH    PM2P-NH    No 
    0x0013    Unassigned 
    0x0014    VRF Recursive NH        VRF-RNH    no 
    0x0015    RT-derived-EC           RT-EC      no 
       
              </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
          </section> 
        </section> 

        <section title="Interactions between Flow Spec Extended Community Actions (FS-EC)"> 
          <t>Interactions between FS-EC only occur if a filter match has
          multiple actions.  If multiple FS-EC actions are listed on a filter,
          these can interact within categories or if a previous FS-EC action
          fails.  Consider three cases of multiple actions as you read this
          section.</t> 

          <t>Case 1: a filter match has three actions:
            <list>
              <t>1. set a DSCP value in the IP Packet,</t>
              <t>2. Sample the traffic (for spam checking), and</t>
              <t>3. Redirect the traffic to a VRF.</t>
            </list>
          </t> 
          <t>Case 2: a filter match has two actions. 
            <list>
              <t>1. redirect to VRF,</t>
              <t>2. TAIS Terminate FS filter processing</t>
            </list> 
          </t>
          <t>Case 3: a Filter match has two actions
            <list>
              <t>1. redirect to VRF, and</t>
              <t>2. redirect to SFC</t>
            </list>
          </t> 

          <section title="Interactions Between Multiple Actions by Categories">
            <t>This section considers interactions between multiple successful
            FSv2 Actions.</t>

            <t>FS-EC actions fall into the following categories:  
              <list>
                <t>1. limitation on filters or actions (interface-set or local configuration)</t> 
                <t>2. rate limiting (bytes (TRB) and packets (TRP)),</t>
                <t>3. Set DSCP value in IP packet</t>
                <t>4. Sample packet (TAIS - sample)</t>
                <t>5. redirect to IP paths  (to VRF, to VPN, to Indirection-ID, to SFC path)</t>
                <t>6. Terminate action processing (TAIS terminate)</t>
              </list> 

            If multiple actions with only one action per category, then there
            is little interaction between successful actions.  If multiple
            actions have more than one action per category, then successful
            actions can interact. For example, the multiple actions in Case 1
            and Case 2 described above only have one type of action per
            category.  In contrast, Case 3 has two interactions in the
            redirect category.</t>

            <t>For multiple actions passed in the FS-EC, this logical
            categorization allow the implementation to reject a set of multiple
            actions if some of the actions interact in a set. Using the three
            case examples, Case 1 and Case 2 FS-EC would be allowed and Case 3
            FS-AC would be rejected.</t> 

            <t>FSv2 actions passed in a BGP Community Attribute can provide
            ordering of actions, dependencies or signal which actions are valid
            within a category
            (see <xref target="I-D.hares-idr-fsv2-more-ip-actions"></xref>).  
            However, these features are beyond the Basic FSv2 for IP forwarding
            and out of scope for this specification.</t>
          </section> 

          <section title="Failure of an FS-EC Action" >
            <t>If multiple FS-EC action is attached to a Flow Spec filter rule and  
            one of the actions fails there are three potential options: 
              <list>
                <t>Option 1. Stop processing additional filters and (optionally) signal failure to the management process,  </t>
                <t>Option 2. Continue on processing in "best effort" for the next filters. </t> 
                <t>Option 3. Decide between 1 and 2 based on dependencies between filters and actions </t>
              </list>
            Option 1 and 2 can be signaled by configuration within a Flow
            Specification implementation.  Option 3 requires the encoding
            dependency lists in ordered filters and ordered actions.  The FSv2
            NLRI format has a field to carry filter dependency information, but
            these funtions are beyond the FSv2 Basic IP functions and out of
            scope for this specification.</t>

            <t>Consider Case 1 where the set DSCP value in IP field fails to occur. 
            Option 1, would be to stop processing and not do the other two actions.  
            Option 2, would be to continue prcoessing and do the other two actions.</t>

            <t>Currently, for FSv1 local configuration determines what happens
            if one of the actions fails within a set of multiple actions
            attached to a filter rule.</t>

            <t>One option for FSv2 is to pass another FS-EC indicating what the
            originator expects will happen upon failure of an action.</t>
          </section> 

          <section title="Action Chain Ordering FSv2-EC (ACO) (optional)">
            <t>
              <dl>
                <dt>Summary:</dt>
                <dd>>This optional FSv2-EC passes information on what the BGP
                peer originating the FSv2-EC expects will happen with multiple
                actions attached to a single filter.</dd>

                  <dt>Description:</dt>
                  <dd>The BGP peer originating multiple FSv2 FS-EC actions
                  attached to FSv2 NLRI (filters) may attach the Action Chain
                  Ordering (ACO) FS-EC to inform BGP Peers receiving the FSv2
                  information how the originating pair expects action
                  interactions and actions failures will be handled. Two fields
                  are encoded in this FS-EC: 

                  <list>
                    <t>AC-interaction - What happens if two actions are
                    specified in a category, and</t>

                    <t>AC-Failure - what happens if an action with multiple
                    action set fails.</t>
                  </list>
                </dd>

                <dt>Encoding:</dt>
                <dd>The Generic Transitive encoding is shown in figure 3-11
                with the field definitions below.</dd>
              </dl>
            </t>
            <t>
              <figure>
              <artwork>
     Generic Transitive Extended Community (IPv4)
     
       0                   1                   2                   3
      0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |  Type high    |  Type low     |AC-interaction |  AC-Failure   |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |        Reserved  (4 octets)                                   |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     
                      Figure 3-11 
              </artwork> 
              </figure> 
            </t>

            <t>where: 
              <dl>
                <dt>Type high:</dt>
                <dd> This 1 octet field has a value of 0x80 For the Generic
                Transitive EC.</dd>

                <dt>Type low:</dt>
                <dd> This one octet field identifies the ACO-Action.  The value
                is TBD4.</dd> 

                <dt>ACO Dependency</dt>
                <dd>This field indicates whether the FS-EC category order is
                the pre-defined order or an implementation specific order. 

                  <list>
                    <t>0 (default): do not install actions with two actions per
                    category.</t>

                    <t>1 (local config): allow under local configuration</t>
                  </list> 
                </dd>

                <dt>AC-failure –</dt>
                <dd> 1 octet byte that determines the action on failure.
                Actions may succeed or fail and an Action chain must deal with
                it.  The default value stored for an action chain that does not
                have this action chain is “stop on failure”.  where AC-Failure
                types are: 
                  <list>
                    <t> 0x00 – stop on failure of an action </t>
                    <t>0x01 – continue on failure of an action,,</t> 
                  </list>
                </dd>

                <dt>Reserved -</dt>
                <dd>Reserved for future use.  Must be set to all zeros, and
                ignored upon reception.</dd>
              </dl>
            </t> 
          </section>
        </section> 
      </section> 
    </section> 

    <section title="Validation and Ordering of NLRI">
      <section title="Validation of FSv2 NLRI ">
        <t>The validation of FSv2 NLRI adheres to the combination of rules for
        general BGP FSv1 NLRI found in <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>, <xref
        target="RFC8956"></xref>, <xref target="RFC9117"></xref>.  These FSv1
        rules are sufficient for FSv2 for IP traffic.</t>

        <t> Specific additions have been defined for IP Filters used for
        guiding IP traffic into Service Function Service Function Pathways SFC
        NLRI in <xref target="RFC9015"></xref>, or validation of L2VPN FS NLRI
        (see <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-l2vpn"></xref>).  These
        additions are not required for the FSv2 for IP Basic functions.
        Therefore, FSv2 NLRI validation for Basic IP uses the same rules as
        FSv1.</t>

        <t>To provide clarity, the full validation process for flow
        specification routes (FSv1 or FSv2) for all AFI/SAFIs is described
        below in section x.x rather than simply referring to the relevant
        portions of these RFCs.  Validation only occurs after BGP UPDATE
        message reception and the FSv2 NLRI and the path attributes relating to
        FSv2 (Extended community and Wide Community) have been determined to be
        well-formed.  Any MALFORMED FSv2 NRLI is handled as a “session reset”
        <xref target="RFC7606"></xref>.</t>

        <section title="Validation of FS NLRI (FSv1 or FSv2)">
          <t> Flow specifications received from a BGP peer that are accepted in
          the respective Adj-RIB-In are used as input to the route selection
          process.  Although the forwarding attributes of the two routes for
          tbe same prefix may be the same, BGP is still required to perform its
          path selection algorithm in order to select the correct set of
          attributes to advertise.</t>

          <t>The first step of the BGP Route selection procedure (section 9.1.2
          of <xref target="RFC4271"></xref> is to exclude from the selection
          procedure routes that are considered unfeasible. In the context of IP
          routing information, this is used to validate that the NEXT_HOP
          Attribute of a given route is resolvable.</t>

          <t>The concept can be extended in the case of the Flow Specification
          NLRI to allow other validation procedures.</t>

          <t>The FSv2 validation process validates the FSv2 NLRI with following
          unicast routes received over the same AFI (1 or 2) but different
          SAFIs:

            <dl>
              <dt>FSv2 received over SAFI=TBD1</dt>
              <dd> FSv1 received over SAFI=133 are be validated against SAFI=1.
              Similarly, FSv2 routes received over SAFI=TBD1 will be validated
              against SAFI=1.</dd>

              <dt>FSv2 received over SAFI=TBD2</dt>
              <dd>FSv1 received over SAFI=134 are validated against SAFI=128,
              and FSv2 received over SAFI=TBD2 will be validated against
              SAFI=128.</dd>

              <dt>FSv2 received with AFI = 31</dt>
              <dd> The FSV2 routes received with (AFI=31, SAFI=TBD1) will be
              validated against SAFI=1.  The FSv2 received with (AFI=31,
              SAFI=TBD2) will be validated against SAFI=128.</dd>

              <dt>FSv2 L2 routes passed in (AFI=6, SAFI=TBD1) and L2VPN routes
              passed in (AFI=25, SAFI=TBD2).</dt>
              <dd>
                <dl> 
                  <dt>FSv2 L2 routes -</dt>
                  <dd> validate (AFI=6, SAFI=TBD1) against (AFI=1, SAFI=1).</dd>

                  <dt>FSv2 L2VPN routes -</dt>
                  <dd> validate (AFI=256, SAFI=TBD2) against (AFI=1, SAFI=128></dd>

                  <dt>This is similar to FSv1. -</dt>
                  <dd> The FSv1 L2 validated L2 routes passed in (AFI=6,
                  SAFI=133) against (AFI=1, SAFI=1) and the L2VPN routes
                  (AFI=25, SAFI=134) are validated against (AFI=1, SAFI=128).</dd>
                </dl>
              </dd>
            </dl>
          </t>

          <t>In the absence of explicit configuration, a Flow specification
          NLRI (FSv1 or FSv2) MUST be validated such that it is considered
          feasible if and only if all of the conditions are true:

            <list>
              <t>a) A destination prefix component is embedded in the Flow
              Specification,</t>
              <t>b) One of the following conditions holds true:

                <list>
                  <t>1. The originator of the Flow Specification matches the
                  originator of the best-match unicast route for the destination
                  prefix embedded in the flow specification (this is the unicast
                  route with the longest possible prefix length covering the
                  destination prefix embedded in the flow specification).</t>

                  <t>2. The AS_PATH attribute of the flow specification is empty
                  or contains only an AS_CONFED_SEQUENCE segment
                  <xref target="RFC5065"></xref>.

                    <list>
                      <t>2a.This condition should be enabled by default.</t>
                      <t>2b.This condition may be disabled by explicit
                      configuration on a BGP Speaker,</t>
                      <t>2c.As an extension to this rule, a given non-empty
                      AS_PATH (besides AS_CONFED_SEQUENCE segments) MAY be
                      permitted by policy].</t>
                    </list> 
                  </t>
                </list>
              </t>

              <t>c) There are no “more-specific” unicast routes when compared
              with the flow destination prefix that have been received from a
              different neighbor AS than the best-match unicast route, which
              has been determined in rule b.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>However, part of rule a may be relaxed by explicit configuration,
          permitting Flow Specifications that include no destination prefix
          component.  If such is the case, rules b and c are moot and MUST be
          disregarded.</t>

          <t>By “originator” of a BGP route, we mean either the address of the
          originator in the ORIGINATOR_ID Attribute
          <xref target="RFC4456"></xref> or the source address of the BGP peer,
          if this path attribute is not present.</t>

          <t>A BGP implementation MUST enforce that the AS in the left-most
          position of the AS_PATH attribute of a Flow Specification Route (FSv1
          or FSv2) received via the Exterior Border Gateway Protocol (eBGP)
          matches the AS in the left-most position of the AS_PATH attribute of
          the best-match unicast route for the destination prefix embedded in
          the Flow Specification (FSv1 or FSv2) NLRI.</t>

          <t>The best-match unicast route may change over time independently of
          the Flow Specification NLRI (FSv1 or FSv2). Therefore, a revalidation
          of the Flow Specification MUST be performed whenever unicast routes
          change.  Revalidation is defined as retesting rules a to c as
          described above.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Validation of Flow Specification Actions for FSv2 for IP Basic">
          <t>A match on a Flow Specification (FS) filters is linked to one or
          more FS action set by an Extended Communities (FS-EC) for FSv2 for IP
          Basic functions.</t>

          <t>Validation of FS-EC action begins with validating the syntax of
          the Extended Communities attributes attached to FS NLRI in UPDATE
          packet.  Since FSv1 and FSv2 operate on different NLRIs (AFI/SAFI
          sets), a single FS-EC action can apply to both FSv1 and FSv2 filters.
          If the FS-EC is not syntactically correct, the FS-EC community causes
          NLRI and FS-EC to be treated as withdrawal.</t> 

          <t>If the FS-EC is syntacically correct, then the FS-EC check to
          determine if this node can perform this action. If not, the FS-EC is
          stored for transmittal to other nodes, but cannot be used in this
          node.</t>

          <t>If multiple syntactically correct actions that can be performed on
          are linked to the filtering rules defined in the NLRI in UPDATE
          packet, then the list of multiple actions are check for conflicts
          within a category. If conflicts exist within a multiple action set
          attached to a FSv2 filter, then the default case is to ignore the
          action set for installation in the node.  Optionally, if the ACO
          FS-EC may indicate if the BGP peer originating the FSv2 filter +
          action expects this "ignoring" of the action or specifical local
          configuration.</t>

          <t>An example of local configuration might be if rate limiting by
          byte and by packet are specified, the local configuration might allow
          both to be enacted in the hardware.</t> 
        </section> 

        <section title="Failure of FS-EC action when processing a filter flow">
          <t>If one action in the ordered list fails for a traffic flow, the
          local node may be able to halt processing of the for. For example, if
          a DSCP value set and forwarding to VPN is specified AND the DSCP
          fails, the forwarding logic may allow the forwarding to the VPN to
          not occur.</t>

          <t>FSv1-EC current control the failure action by configuration and/or
          implementation defaults.</t>

          <t>The optional ACO FSv2-EC can inform the BGP receiving the FSv2
          information how the originator expects failures within the multiple
          actions in an action set will occur.  The ACO FSv2-EC is optional.</t> 

          <t>FSv2 Implementations MAY wish to log the action failures
          encountered by FS actions (FSv1 or FSv2).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Error handling and Validation">
          <t>The following two error handling rules must be followed by all BGP
          speakers which support FSv2:

            <list style="symbols">
              <t>FSv2 NLRI having TLVs which do not have the correct lengths or
              syntax must be considered MALFORMED, and "treated-as-withdrawl".</t>

              <t>FSv2 NLRIs having TLVs which do not follow the above ordering
              rules described in section 4.1 MUST be considered as MALFORMED by
              a BGP FSv2 propagator, and treated "treated-as-withdrawl".</t>
            </list>

          The above two rules prevent any ambiguity that arises from the
          multiple copies of the same NLRI from multiple BGP FSv2 propagators.</t>

          <t>A BGP implementation SHOULD treat such malformed NLRIs as ‘session
          reset’ <xref target="RFC7606"></xref></t>

          <t>An implementation for a BGP speaker supporting both FSv1 and FSv2
          MUST support the error handling for both FSv1 and FSv2.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section title="Ordering of FS filters for BGP Peers which support FSv1 and FSv2">
        <t> FSv2 allows the user to order flow specification rules and the
        actions associated with a rule. Each FSv2 rule has one or more match
        conditions and one or more actions associated with each rule.</t>

        <t>FSv1 and FSv2 filters are sent as different AFI/SAFI pairs so FSv1
        and FSv2 operate as ships-in-the-night.  Some BGP peers in an AS may
        support both FSv1 and FSv2.  Other BGP peers may support FSv1 or FSv2.
        Some BGP will not support FSv1 or FSV2.  A coherent flow specification
        technology must have consistent best practices for ordering the FSv1
        and FSv2 filter rules.</t>

        <t>One simple rule captures the best practice:  Order the FSv1 filters
        after the FSv2 filter by placing the FSv1 filters after the FSv2
        filters.</t>

        <t>To operationally make this work, all flow specification filters
        should be included the same data base with the FSv1 filters being
        assigned a user- defined order beyond the normal size of FSv2
        user-ordered values.  A few examples, may help to illustrate this best
        practice.</t>

        <t>Example 1: User ordered numbering - Suppose you might have 1,000
        rules for the FSv2 filters.  Assign all the FSv1 user defined rules to
        1,001 (or better yet 2,000).  The FSv1 rules will be ordered by the
        components and component values.</t>

        <t>Example 2: Storage of actions - All FSv1 actions are defined ordered
        actions in FSv2.  Translate your FSv1 actions into FSv2 ordered actions
        for storing in a common FSv1-FSv2 flow specification data base.</t>
      </section>
    </section> 

    <section title="Scalability and Aspirations for FSv2">
      <t>Operational issues drive the deployment of BGP flow specification as a
      quick and scalable way to distribute filters.  The early operations
      accepted the fact validation of the distribution of filter needed to be
      done outside of the BGP distribution mechanism.  Other mechanisms
      (NETCONF/RESTCONF or PCEP) have reply-request protocols.</t>

      <t>These features within BGP have not changed. BGP still does not have an
      action-reply feature.</t>

      <t>NETCONF/RESTCONF latest enhancements provide action/response features
      which scale.  The combination of a quick distribution of filters via BGP
      and a long-term action in NETCONF/RESTCONF that ask for reporting of the
      installation of FSv2 filters may provide the best scalability.</t>

      <t>The combination of NETCONF/RESTCONF network management protocols and
      BGP focuses each protocol on the strengths of scalability.</t>

      <t>FSv2 will be deployed in webs of BGP peers which have some BGP peers
      passing FSv1, some BGP peers passing FSv2, some BGP peers passing FSv1
      and FSv2, and some BGP peers not passing any routes.</t>

      <t>The TLV encoding and deterministic behaviors of FSv2 will not
      deprecate the need for careful design of the distribution of flow
      specification filters in this mixed environment.  The needs of networks
      for flow specification are different depending on the network topology
      and the deployment technology for BGP peers sending flow specification.</t>

      <t>Suppose we have a centralized RR connected to DDoS processing sending
      out flow specification to a second tier of RR who distribute the
      information to targeted nodes. This type of distribution has one set of
      needs for FSv2 and the transition from FSv1 to FSv2.</t>

      <t>Suppose we have Data Center with a 3-tier backbone trying to
      distribute DDoS or other filters from the spine to combinational nodes,
      to the leaf BGP nodes.  The BGP peers may use RR or normal BGP
      distribution. This deployment has another set of needs for FSv2 and the
      transition from FSv1 to FSV2.</t>

      <t>Suppose we have a corporate network with a few AS sending DDoS filters
      using basic BGP from a variety of sites. Perhaps the corporate network
      will be satisfied with FSv1 for a long time.</t> 

      <t>These examples are given to indicate that BGP FSv2, like so many BGP
      protocols, needs to be carefully tuned to aid the mitigation services
      within the network. This protocol suite starts the migration toward
      better tools using FSv2, but it does not end it.  With FSv2 TLVs and
      deterministic actions, new operational mechanisms can start to be
      understood and utilized.</t>

      <t>This FSv2 specification is merely the start of a revolution of work –
      not the end.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Optional Security Additions">
      <t>This section discusses the optional BGP Security additions for BGP-FS
      v2 relating ROA <xref target="RFC9582"></xref>.</t> 

      <section title="BGP FSv2 with ROA">
        <t>BGP FSv2 can utilize ROAs in the validation. If BGP FSv2 is used
        with BGPSEC and ROA, the first thing is to validate the route within
        BGPSEC and second to utilize BGP ROA to validate the route origin.</t>

        <t> The BGP-FS peers using both ROA and BGP-FS validation determine
        that a BGP Flow specification is valid if and only if one of the
        following cases: 
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>If the BGP Flow Specification NLRI has a IPv4 or IPv6 address in
            destination address match filter and the following is true:

              <list style="symbols">
                <t>A BGP ROA has been received to validate the originator, and</t>

                <t>The route is the best-match unicast route for the
                destination prefix embedded in the match filter; or</t>
              </list>
            </t>

            <t>If a BGP ROA has not been received that matches the IPv4 or IPv6
            destination address in the destination filter, the match filter
            must abide by the <xref target="RFC8955"></xref> and
            <xref target="RFC8956"></xref> validation rules as follows:  
              <list>
                <t>The originator match of the flow specification matches the
                originator of the best-match unicast route for the destination
                prefix filter embedded in the flow specification", and</t>

                <t>No more specific unicast routes exist when compared with the
                flow destination prefix that have been received from a
                different neighboring AS than the best-match unicast route,
                which has been determined in step A.</t>
              </list>
            </t>
          </list>
        The best match is defined to be the longest-match NLRI with the highest
        preference.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This section complies with <xref target="RFC7153"></xref>.</t>

      <section title="Flow Specification V2 SAFIs">
        <t> IANA is requested to assign two SAFI Values in the registry at
        https://www.iana.org/assignments/safi-namespace from the Standard Action
        Range as follows: 
          <figure>
          <artwork>
       
         Table 7-1 SAFIs 
            
         Value   Description      Reference
         -----   -------------    ---------------
          TBD1   BGP FSv2        [this document] 
          TBD2   BGP FSv2 VPN    [this document]

          </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="BGP Capability Code">
        <t>IANA is requested to assign a Capability Code from the registry at
        https://www.iana.org/assignments/capability-codes/ from the IETF Review
        range as follows:

        <figure>
        <artwork>     
       Table 7-2 - Capability Code 
       
       Value   Description            Reference       Controller
       -----  ---------------------  ---------------  ----------
        TBD3  Flow Specification V2  [this document]  IETF
        </artwork>
        </figure>
       </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Generic Transitive Extended Community">
        <t>IANA is requested to assign a type value from the "Generic
        Transitive Extended Community Sub-Types" registry at
        https://www.iana.org/assignments/bgp-extended-communities/bgp-extended-communities.xhtml  

          <figure>
          <artwork>     
       Table 7-3 - Generic Transitive Extended Community 
       
       Value   Description                Reference       Controller
       -----  --------------------------  ---------------  ----------
        TBD4  FSv2 Action Chain Ordering  [this document]  IETF
            
       The requested value is "0x01".  
          </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="FSv2 IP Filters Component Types">
        <t>IANA is requested to create a new "BGP FSv2 Component Types"
        registry and indicate [this draft] as a reference.  The following
        assignments in the FSv2 IP Filters Component Types Registry shold be
        made.</t>

        <t>
          <figure>
          <artwork>
       Table 7-5 - Flow Specification 

       Registry Name: BGP FSv2 Component Types 
       Reference: [this document]
       Registration Procedures: 0x01-0x3FFF Standards Action. 
     
       Value  Description         Reference        
       -----  ------------------- ------------------------
        1     Destination filter  [RFC8955][RFC8956][this document] 
        2     Source Prefix       [RFC8955][RFC8956][this document] 
        3     IP Protocol         [RFC8955][RFC8956][this document] 
        4     Port                [RFC8955][RFC8956][this document]   
        5     Destination Port    [RFC8955][RFC8956][this document] 
        6     Source Port         [RFC8955][RFC8956][this document] 
        7     ICMP Type [v4 or v6][RFC8955][RFC8956][this document] 
        8     ICMP Code [v4 or v6][RFC8955][RFC8956][this document] 
        9     TCP Flags [v4]      [RFC8955][RFC8956][this document] 
       10     Packet Length       [RFC8955][RFC8956][this document] 
       11     DSCP marking        [RFC8955][RFC8956][this document] 
       12     Fragment            [RFC8955][RFC8956][this document] 
       13     Flow Label          [RFC8956][this document] 
          </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="FSV2 NLRI TLV Types ">
        <t>IANA is requested to create the a new registries on a new "Flow
        Specification v2 TLV Types” web page.</t>

        <t>This set of option assumes Type 2 ordering by packet frame rather
        than ascending order. 

        <figure>
        <artwork>
       Table 7-6 FSv2 TLV types - Option 2 
       Registry Name: BGP FSv2 TLV types 
       Reference: [this document]
       Registration Procedures: 0x01-0x3FFF Standards Action.
       
      
        Type          Description              Reference
        ----          ----------------------   ------------
        0x00          Reserved                 [this document]
            0x01-0x31     Unassigned               [this document] 
            0x32 (50)     L2 Traffic Rules         [this document] 
            0x33-0x63     Unassigned               [this document] 
            0x64 (100)    MPLS traffic rules         [this document] 
            0x65 (101)    Unassigned               [this document]
         -0x95 (149)          
            0x96 (150)    SFC Traffic rules        [this document]
        0x97 (151)    Unassigned               [this document] 
         - 0xC7         
        0xC8 (200)    Tunnel Traffic rules     [this document]         
            0xC9-0x99     Unassigned               [this document] 
            0x100 (256)   IP traffic rules         [this document]
             0x101-0x117  Unassigned 
             
        0x118 (280)   Extended IP Rules        [this document]
             0x119-0x6000 Unassigned               [this document]
             
        0x6000-0x7FFF Vendor specific          [this document]
        0x8000-0xFFFF Reserved                 [this document]

          </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section> 

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The use of ROA improves on <xref target="RFC8955"></xref> by checking
      to see of the route origination. This check can improve the validation
      sequence for a multiple-AS environment.</t>

      <t>>The use of BGPSEC  <xref target="RFC8205"></xref> to secure the
      packet can increase security of BGP flow specification information sent
      in the packet.</t>

      <t>The use of the reduced validation within an AS
      <xref target="RFC9117"></xref> can provide adequate validation for
      distribution of flow specification within a single autonomous system for
      prevention of DDoS.</t>

      <t>Distribution of flow filters may provide insight into traffic being
      sent within an AS, but this information should be composite information
      that does not reveal the traffic patterns of individuals.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.0791"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4360"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4456"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4760"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5065"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5701"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7153"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7606"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8955"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8956"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9015"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9117"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9582"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-l2vpn"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-nvo3"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-srv6"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-interfaceset"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-redirect-ip"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-path-redirect"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-wide-bgp-communities"/>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6241"/> 
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8040"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8205"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-v2"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.hares-idr-fsv2-more-ip-actions"/>
      <!-- xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.hares-idr-fsv2-more-ip-filters"/-->
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
