<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc consensus="yes" ?>
<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="std"
  docName="draft-ietf-idr-fsv2-ip-basic-04"
  submissionType="IETF"
  ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="BGP FSv2 Basic IP">BGP Flow Specification Version 2 - for Basic IP </title>
    <author fullname="Susan Hares" initials="S" surname="Hares">
      <organization>Hickory Hill Consulting</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>7453 Hickory Hill</street>
          <city>Saline</city>
          <region>MI</region>
          <code>48176</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1-734-604-0332</phone>
        <email>shares@ndzh.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Donald Eastlake" initials="D" surname="Eastlake">
      <organization>Independent</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
        <street>2386 Panoramic Circle</street>
          <city>Apopka</city>
          <region>FL</region>
          <code>32703</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1-508-333-2270</phone>
        <email>d3e3e3@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Jie Dong" initials="J" surname="Dong" >
      <organization> Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>No. 156 Beiqing Road</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jie.dong@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Chaitanya Yadlapalli" initials="C" surname="Yadlapalli">
      <organization>ATT</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>cy098d@att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Sven Maduschke" initials="S" surname="Maduscke" >
      <organization> Verizon</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>DE</country>
        </postal>
        <email>sven.maduschke@de.verizon.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Jeff Haas" initials="J" surname="Haas" >
      <organization> HPE</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jeffrey.haas@hpe.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" />
    <area>Routing Area</area>
    <workgroup>IDR Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>RFC</keyword>
    <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>
    <keyword>I-D</keyword>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>BGP FSv2 - IP Basic</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>BGP flow specification version 1 (FSv1), defined in RFC 8955, RFC
      8956, and RFC 9117, describes the distribution of traffic filter policy
      (traffic filters and actions) distributed via BGP. During the deployment
      of BGP FSv1 a number of issues were detected, so version 2 of the BGP
      flow specification (FSv2) protocol addresses these issues.  In order to
      provide a clear demarcation between FSv1 and FSv2, a different NLRI
      encapsulates FSv2.</t>

      <t>The IDR WG requires two implementation. Early feedback on
      implementations of FSv2 indicate that FSv2 has a correct design
      direction, but that breaking FSv2 into a progression of documents would
      aid deployment of the draft (basic, adding more filters, and adding more
      actions). This document specifies the basic FSv2 NLRI with user ordering
      of filters added to FSv1 IP Filters and FSv2 actions.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Version 2 of BGP flow specification was original defined in
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-v2"></xref> (BGP FSv2).</t>

      <t>FSv2 is an update to BGP Flow specification version 1 (BGP FSv1).  BGP
      FSv1 as defined in <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>,
      <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>, and <xref target="RFC9117"></xref>
      specified 2 SAFIs (133, 134) to be used with IPv4 AFI (AFI = 1) and IPv6
      AFI (AFI=2).</t>

      <t>The initial BGP FSv2 specification had the correct direction, but it
      contained more than the early implementers desired. The implmenters desired a
      progression of documents with smaller incremental changes: Basic FSv2,
      adding more filters, and adding more actions.</t>

      <t>This draft provides the basic FSv2 framework
      specification for transmitting user-ordered IP filters in the FSV2 NLRI
      and associating Flow Spec actions by transmitting Flow Spec Extended
      Communities (FS-EC) with the FSv2 NLRI.  If a filter match links to a single
      FS-EC action, the single action succeeds or fails. If a filter match
      links to mutiple actions, there is a potential for interactions.
      <xref target="fs-interactions"/>
      discusses how to analyze the interaction by categories and solutions
      to issues with multiple FSv2-EC actions interacting. A complete solution
      requires the BGP Community Container Attribute see
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-wide-bgp-communities"></xref>) with FSv2
      Container defined in the
      <xref target="I-D.hares-idr-fsv2-more-ip-actions"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This document defines 2 new SAFIs, TBD1 and TBD2, for FSv2 to be used
      with 5 AFIs: 1, 2, 6, 25, and 31.  FSv2 implementations do not
      require all 10 combinations of FSv2 AFI/SAFIs to be implemented.
      An implementation is required to implement only one these
      AFI/SAFIs to be compliant.  For example, a compliant implementation
      might only define the FSv2 NLRI for IPv4 for IP forwarding (AFI=1,
      SAFI=TBD1).</t>

      <t>FSv1 and FSv2 use different AFI/SAFIs to send their respective flow
      specification filters.  This permits FSv1 and FSv2 to be coexist with
      each other in a "ships in the night" deployment.</t>

      <t>The remainder of <xref target="intro"/> provides background on why the
      FSv2 was necessary to fix problems with FSv1.
      <xref target="fsv2-primer"/>  contains a primer on FSv2.
      <xref target="fsv2-formats-and-actions"/> contains the BGP encoding rules
      for FSv2.  <xref target="fsv2-validation-and-ordering"/> describes how
      to validate and order FSv2 NLRI.  The remaining sections discuss
      scalability, optional security additions, security considerations, and
      IANA considerations.</t>

      <section anchor="introFSv2" title="Why Flow Specification v2">
        <t>Modern IP routers have the capability to forward traffic and to
        classify, shape, rate limit, filter, or redirect packets based on
        administratively defined policies. These traffic policy mechanisms
        allow the operator to define match rules that operate on multiple
        fields within header of an IP data packet.  The traffic policy allows
        actions to be taken upon a match to be associated with each match rule.
        These rules can be more widely defined as "event-condition-action"
        (ECA) rules where the event is always the reception of a packet.</t>

        <t>BGP (<xref target="RFC4271"></xref>) flow specification version 1 (FSv1) as defined
        by <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>, <xref target="RFC8956"></xref>,
        and <xref target="RFC9117"></xref> specifies the distribution of traffic
        filter policy (traffic filters and actions) via BGP to BGP
        peers, both IBGP and EBGP.  The traffic filter is applied when
        packets are received on a router with the flow specification function
        enabled.</t>

        <t>Multiple deployed applications currently use BGP FSv1 to distribute
        traffic filters.  These applications include:

          <ul>
            <li>Mitigation of Denial of Service traffic (DoS).</li>
            <li>Traffic filtering in BGP/MPLS VPNS.</li>
            <li>Centralized traffic control for networks utilizing SDN control
            of router firewall functions.</li>
            <li>Classifiers for insertion into a SFC.</li>
            <li>Filters for SRv6 (segment routing v6).</li>
          </ul>
        </t>

        <t>During the deployment of FSv1, the following issues were noted:

          <ul>
            <li>FSv1 NLRI components did not use TLV encoding, which inhibited
            defining new component types. (The format was type-value, missing a
            length field.)</li>
            <li>FSv1 rules did not have the ability to be ordered by the
            operator. Instead, only the protocol-defined rule ordering was
            permitted.</li>
            <li>When conflicting outcomes for rule actions was present, the
            operator was unable to influence their ordering.</li>
            <li>When multiple and conflicting rule actions were present, the
            operator couldn't define their order when some actions could not be
            implemented on the receiving router.</li>
          </ul>
        </t>

        <t>Networks currently address these issues by constraining
        deployments or using topology/deployment specific workarounds.</t>

        <t>FSv1 is a critical component of deployed applications. Therefore,
        this specification defines how FSv2 will interact with BGP peers that
        support combinations FSv1 and FSv2. It is expected that a
        transition to FSv2 will occur over time as new applications require
        features enabled by FSv2.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Definitions and Acronyms">
        <t>
          <dl newline="true">
          <dt>AFI:</dt>
          <dd>Address Family Identifier <xref target="RFC4760"/></dd>

          <dt>AS:</dt>
          <dd>Autonomous System</dd>

          <dt>BGP session ephemeral state:</dt>
          <dd>State which does not survive the loss of BGP peer session.</dd>

          <dt>BGP Commmunity Path Attribute:</dt>
          <dd>BGP Community Path attribute with a FS TLV defined by
          <xref target="I-D.hares-idr-fsv2-more-ip-actions"></xref></dd>

          <dt>Configuration state:</dt>
          <dd>State which persist across a reboot of software module within a
          routing system or a reboot of a hardware routing device.</dd>

          <dt>CPA:</dt>
          <dd>BGP Community Path Attribute.</dd>

          <dt>DDoS:</dt>
          <dd>Distributed Denial of Service.</dd>

          <dt>Ephemeral state:</dt>
          <dd>State which does not survive the reboot of a software module, or
          a hardware reboot. Ephemeral state can be ephemeral configuration
          state or operational state.</dd>

          <dt>Extended Community:</dt>
          <dd>BGP Path Attribute defined by <xref target="RFC4360"/>.</dd>

          <dt>FS:</dt>
          <dd>Flow Specification (either v1 or v2).</dd>

          <dt>FSv1:</dt>
          <dd>Flow Specification version 1 <xref target="RFC8955"/>
          <xref target="RFC8956"/>.</dd>

          <dt>FSv2:</dt>
          <dd>Flow Specification version 2 (this document and its extensions).</dd>

          <dt>FS-CPA:</dt>
          <dd>Flow Specification Actions defined in Community Path Attribute.</dd>

          <dt>FS-EC:</dt>
          <dd>FS related Extended Community with FS actions.</dd>

          <dt>FSv1-EC:</dt>
          <dd>FSv1 Extended Community with FS Actions supported by FSv1.</dd>

          <dt>FSv2-EC:</dt>
          <dd>FSv2 Extended Community with FS Actions supported by FSv2.</dd>

          <dt>NETCONF:</dt>
          <dd>The Network Configuration Protocol <xref target="RFC6241"/>.</dd>

          <dt>NLRI:</dt>
          <dd>Network Layer Reachability Information <xref target="RFC4271"/>
          <xref target="RFC4760"/>.  The "destination" portion of a Flowspec
          route carried in a BGP UPDATE message.</dd>

          <dt>RESTCONF:</dt>
          <dd>The RESTCONF Protocol <xref target="RFC8040"/>.</dd>

          <dt>RIB:</dt>
          <dd>Routing Information Base.</dd>

          <dt>ROA:</dt>
          <dd>Route Origin Authentication <xref target="RFC9582"/>.</dd>

          <dt>RR:</dt>
          <dd>Route Reflector <xref target="RFC4456"/>.</dd>

          <dt>SAFI:</dt>
          <dd>Subsequent Address Family Identifier <xref target="RFC4760"/>.</dd>

          <dt>SFC:</dt>
          <dd>Service Function Chaining <xref target="RFC7665"/>.</dd>
          </dl>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref
        target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and only
        when, they appear in all capitals as shown here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="fsv2-primer" title="Flow Specification Version 2 Primer ">
      <t>A BGP Flow Specification (v1 or v2) is an n-tuple containing one or
      more match criteria that can be applied to data-plane traffic.  The
      exact traffic match depends on the FSv2 AFI/SAFI.</t>

      <t>Flows Specification routes carried in BGP UPDATEs may carry BGP Path
      Attributes that have additional match or action consequences.  This
      includes, but is not limited to: Extended Communities
      <xref target="RFC4360"/> and Community Container Path attributes
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-wide-bgp-communities"/>.</t>

      <t>Flow Specifiation NLRI for a given AFI/SAFI is used as they key for
      Flow Specification routes in the BGP RIBs.  Flow Specification routes
      that are selected for the Loc-RIB are then associated with a given set of
      semantics which are application dependent. Standard BGP policy mechanisms
      for BGP routes are applicable to Flow Specification routes, including
      AS_PATH and community filtering.</t>

      <t>This FSv2 for basic IP forwarding specification only requires the use
      of Extended Communities to associate FS actions with FSv2 filters found in
      FSv2 NLRI.</t>

      <t>FSv2 features implementing multiple actions with user ordering of actions or
      dependencies between actions requires the BGP Community Attribute
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-wide-bgp-communities"></xref> with a FSv2
      Component as defined in <xref target="I-D.hares-idr-fsv2-more-ip-actions"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Network operators can control the propagation of Flow Specification
      BGP routes by enabling or disabling the exchange of routes for a
      particular AFI/SAFI pair on a particular peering session.  BGP policy
      mechanisms, including <xref target="RFC1997"/> scoping communities, can
      also be used. Thus, Flow Specification routes may be distributed to only
      a portion of a BGP deployment.</t>

      <section title="Flow Specification v1 (FSv1) SAFIs ">
        <t>The FSv1 NLRI defined in <xref target="RFC8955"></xref> and
        <xref target="RFC8956"></xref> includes 13 match conditions encoded for
        the following AFI/SAFIs:

        <list style="symbol">
          <t>IPv4 traffic: AFI:1, SAFI:133 </t>
          <t>IPv6 Traffic: AFI:2, SAFI:133 </t>
          <t>BGP/MPLS IPv4 VPN: AFI:1, SAFI: 134 </t>
          <t>BGP/MPLS IPv6 VPN: AFI:2, SAFI: 134</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>FSv1 match conditions are ordered by component type in ascending
        order.  The ordering within a component type is defined by that
        component's definition.</t>

        <t>The Flow Specification actions standardized by <xref target="RFC8955"/> and
        <xref target="RFC8956"/> are:

          <ul>
            <li>accept packet (default),</li>
            <li>traffic rate limiting by bps (0x6),</li>
            <li>traffic-action: sample, or terminate rule (0x7),</li>
            <li>redirect traffic to VPN by route target(0x8),</li>
            <li>traffic marking (DSCP) (0x9), and </li>
            <li>traffic rate limiting by pps (0xC)</li>
          </ul>
        </t>

        <t>A SFC action <xref target="RFC9015"/> defines a redirection of a
        data flow to an entry point into a specific SFP (Service Function
        Path).</t>

        <t>Other Extended Community actions have been proposed in IDR, but have
        not completed the standardization process.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Transition to FSv2">
        <t>This specification defines AFI/SAFIs to support
        Flow Specification version 2 for IPv4, IPv6, Layer 2, IPv4 VPNs, IPv6
        VPNs, Layer 2 VPNs (L2VPN), Service Function Chaining (SFC), and SFC
        VPNs:

          <ul>
            <li>IPv4 traffic: AFI=1, SAFI=TBD1,</li>
            <li>IPv6 traffic: AFI=2, SAFI=TBD1,</li>
            <li>L2: AFI=6, SAFI=TDB1 (defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-l2vpn"/>),</li>
            <li>BGP/MPLS IPv4 VPN: AFI=1, SAFI=TBD2,</li>
            <li>BGP/MPLS IPv6 VPN: AFI=2, SAFI=TBD2,</li>
            <li>BGP/MPLS L2VPN: AFI=25, SAFI=TDB2 (defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-l2vpn"/>),</li>
            <li>SFC: AFI=31, SAFI=TBD1,</li>
            <li>SFC VPN: AFI=31, SAFI=TBD2</li>
          </ul>
        </t>

        <t>One question asked by developers is what AFI/SAFI is required for
        FSv2 IP Basic compliance.  BGP negotiates support for each AFI/SAFI, so
        FSv2 IP Basic support for non-VPN could be as little as FSv2 for IPv4
        forwarding (AFI/SAFI: 1/TBD1),</t>

        <!-- XXX JMH - this paragraph goes away as we do integration of the other specs later -->
        <t>The IDR specification for L2 VPN traffic was specified in
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-l2vpn"></xref>.  An IDR
        specification for tunneled traffic is in
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-nvo3"></xref>.
        Both of these drafts were targeted for FSv1, but the WG decided to
        require these to FSv2 TLV formats.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="FSv2 Overview">
        <t>FSv2 allows the user to order the flow specification rules and the
        actions associated with a rule. Each FSv2 rule may have one or more
        match conditions and one or more associated actions.</t>

        <t>FSv2 operates in a ships-in-the night model with FSv1. This permits
        operators to manage the interaction of FSv2 and FSv1 via
        configuration.</t>

        <t>The basic principles regarding the ordering and installation of flow
        specification filter rules are:
          <ol>
            <li>In the absence of a matching filter for the traffic, that
            traffic is permitted. That is, the default is permit.
            Implementations MAY implement a default reject behavior by
            configuration.</li>

            <li>FSv2 filter rules are processed prior to FSv1 rules.  FSv1 NLRI
            are processed according to the procedures defined in
            <xref target="RFC8955"/> and <xref target="RFC8956"/>.
            FSv2 filter rules thus have a better precedence vs. FSv1.</li>

            <li>FSv2 filter rules are ordered based on user-specified order,
            carried in each FSv2 NLRI.  Numerically smaller user-specified order
            values have better precedence than larger values.</li>

            <li>For rules with the same user-specified order, the filter rules
            are then ordered by FSv2 component type and then rules for each
            component type.</li>

            <li>
              <t>FSv2 filter rules can carry actions.  These actions can be
              encoded via one or more FSv2 Extended Communities, or within the
              FSv2 Action Community Container.</t>

              <t>Some FSv2 Extended Communities may not be understood by every
              FSv2 implementation.  Since they are encoded as
              <xref target="RFC4360"/> Extended Communities, they are
              propagated with the BGP routes regardless of whether they are
              understood based on the particular Extended Community's
              transitivity.</t>

              <t>When FSv2 Extended Communities are understood, they have
              precedence and interaction rules governing the actions they
              encode. (See XXX JMH TODO)</t>

              <t>The FSv2 Action Community Container defines its own rules
              governing FSv2 actions.  See that document (XXX JMH TODO) for
              additional details.</t>
            </li>

            <li>
              <t>FSv2 filter match and action criteria may be considered
              "optional".  For match, the FSv2 NLRI encoding carries a
              per-component flag set by the operator or implementation that
              marks that match component as optional or mandatory.  For
              actions, FSv2 Extended Communities will document whether they are
              considered optional or mandatory as part of their definition.
              The optionality of FSv2 Action Community Containers is defined in
              its defining document.</t>

              <t>If a mandatory match component or action component cannot be
              locally implemented, the flowspec rule is marked as ineligible to
              be installed.</t>
            </li>

            <li>FSv2 filter rules carry a "Dependency" value in the FSv2 NLRI.
            When this value is non-zero, this value associates multiple received
            FSv2 filters with each other. If a FSv2 filter rule is ineligible
            to be installed due to an inability to implement a mandatory match
            or action component, all other filters carrying the same dendency
            value will be made ineligible for installation. See
            <xref target="fsv2-dependencies"/> for more details.</li>
          </ol>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="fsv2-formats-and-actions" title="FSv2 NLRI Formats and Actions">
      <t>BGP Flow Specifications are encoded in BGP NLRI as an ordered list of
      TLVs of "filter families", where each filter family consists of an
      ordered list of TLVs of "filter components" for that familiy. Filter
      families are groupings of related filtering functionality, typically at
      the same network layer. Filter components match specific network elements
      for a filter family.</t>

      <t>Each FSv2 NLRI has a default sort order, documented in section TODO.
      This sort order determines the order of installation for the Flow
      Specification in the BGP speaker.   Operators <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> override
      this default ordering by causing the FSv2 User Order field to be set to a
      non-zero value.</t>

      <t>Sets of FSv2 NLRI might share fate with each other. In the event that
      a Flow Specification is unable to be installed by the BGP speaker,
      dependent Flow Specifications <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> also be installed,
      even if they are otherwise valid. These dependencies are encoded in the
      Dependent Filters Chain field of a FSv2 Flow Specification.</t>

      <t>FSv2 is carried in BGP using standard <xref target="RFC4760"/>
      multiprotocol extensions.  FSv2 supports NRLI with formats for following AFIs:
	<ul>
	  <li>IPv4 (AFI = 1)</li>
	  <li>IPv6 (AFI = 2)</li>
	  <li>L2 (AFI = 6)</li>
	  <li>L2VPN (AFI=25)</li>
	  <li> SFC (AFI=31)</li>
	</ul>
      </t>
      <t>These AFIs will be paired with the following SAFIs:

	<ul>
	  <li>TBD1 (Flow Spec Version 2)</li>
	  <li>TBD2 (Flow Spec Version 2 for VPNs)</li>
	</ul>
      </t>

      <t>A compliant FSv2 implementation only has to implement one AFI/SAFI
      pair out of the full list of NRLIs.  For example, a compliant FSv2
      implementation might only implement IPv4 FSv2 (AFI=1, SAFI=TBD1).</t>

      <t>FSv2 NLRI are encoded in BGP UPDATEs using the MP_REACH_NLRI and
      MP_UNREACH_NLRI attributes defined in <xref target="RFC4760"/>.  When
      advertising FSv2 NLRI, the length of the Next-Hop Network Address MUST
      be set to 0. Upon reception, the MP_REACH_NLRI "Network Address of
      NextHop" field MUST be ignored.</t>


      <section title="FSv2 NLRI Format">

        <!-- XXX JMH - this is the start of a section describing the top level thinking for why things are organized the way they are -->
        <t>FSv2 Flow Specifications are encoded as an ordered list of TLVs of filter families. FSv2
        filter famliies are typically associated with match criteria for a given
        networking layer; for example, 802.2 Layer 2, MPLS, IPv4/IPv6, Segment
        Routing, etc.</t>

        <!-- XXX JMH - there needs to be a separate definition for the VPN family -->
        <t>The AFI/SAFI NLRI for BGP Flow Specification version 2 (FSv2) has the format:
         <figure title="FSv2 NLRI Format">
         <artwork>
+-------------------------+
| NLRI Length             |
| (2 octets)              |
+-------------------------+
| Dependent Filters Chain |
| (4 octets)              |
+-------------------------+
| User Order              |
| (4 octets)              |
+-------------------------+
| FSv2 Filter Family TLVs |
| (variable)              |
+-------------------------+
          </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>

        <t>Where:
          <ul>
            <li>NLRI Length: Length of the NLRI field in octets excluding the
            NLRI Length field.  The minimum NLRI Length is 8 (Dependent Filter
            Chain + User Order).</li>

            <li>Dependent Filters Chain (DFC): A 32-bit unsigned integer in
            network byte order.  When non-zero, the Dependent Filters Chain
            value is used to associate multiple NLRI together that share
            dependencies.  See <xref target="fsv2-dependencies"/> for further
            information on its use.</li>

            <li>User Order: A 32-bit unsigned integer in network byte order.
            FSv2 rules with a lower User Order value have a better precedence
            for filter ordering.</li>

	    <li>FSv2 Filter Family TLVs: An ordered list of TLVs of FSv2 filter
	    families.  The encoding of these filter families is documented in
	    the next section.</li>
          </ul>
        </t>

	<section anchor="fsv2-filter-families" title="FSv2 Filter Family TLVs">
        <t>Each each FSv2 Filter Family TLV has the format:
          <figure title="FSv2 Filter Family TLV Format">
          <artwork>
+-----------------------------+
| FSv2 Filter Family Type     |
| (2 octets)                  |
+-----------------------------+
| FSv2 Filter Family Length   |
| (2 octets)                  |
+-----------------------------+
| FSv2 Filter Components TLVs |
| (variable)                  |
+-----------------------------+
          </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>

        <t>Where:
          <ul>
	    <li>FSv2 Filter Family Type: A 16-bit unsigned integer in network
	    byte order defining the FSv2 filter that is carried in this TLV.
	    For sorting purposes, lower value FSv2 Filter Types have a better
	    precendence than higher values.</li>

	    <li>FSv2 Filter Family Length: Length of the FSv2 Filter Components
	    TLVs in octets.</li>
	  </ul>
        </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="fsv2-filter-components" title="FSv2 Filter Component TLVs">
        <t>Each each FSv2 Filter Component TLV has the Format:
          <figure title="FSv2 Filter Component TLV Format">
          <artwork>
+------------------------------+
| FSv2 Filter Component Flags  |
| (4 bits)                     |
+------------------------------+
| FSv2 Filter Component Type   |
| (16 bits)                    |
+------------------------------+
| FSv2 Filter Component Length |
| (2 octets)                   |
+------------------------------+
| FSv2 Filter Component Value  |
| (variable)                   |
+------------------------------+
          </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>

        <t>Where:
          <ul>
            <li><t>The FSv2 Filter Component Flags are defined as:
              <figure title="FSv2 Filter Component Flags Format">
              <artwork>
  0   1   2   3  
+---+---+---+---+
| O | R | R | R |
+---+---+---+---+
              </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>

	    <!-- XXX JMH - this probably needs an IANA section -->
            <t>The fields of the FSv2 Filter Component Flags are defined as:
              <ul>
                <li>O - Optional: When 0, the FSv2 filter-type-specific filter
		component is mandatory and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be supported by
		the local implementation.  Otherwise, when 1, the component is
		considered "optional". When the component is mandatory and is
		not supported, the FSv2 filter rule is considered "invalid" for
		validation purposes.</li>

                <li>R - Reserved: When not otherwise re-defined in a later
                document, this bit <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero when sent and
                <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be ignored on reception.</li>
              </ul>
            </t>
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>FSv2 Filter Component Type: A 12-bit unsigned integer in
              network byte order defining the match component for a given FSv2
              filter type.  For sorting purposes, lower value FSv2 Filter
              Component Types have a better precedence than higher values.</t>

              <t>This document defines the following FSv2 Filter Component Types.
              The definition of the type-specific filter components may be defined in
              other documents:

      <!--
            <t>FSv2 Filter type: contains a type for FSv2 TLV format of the
            NRLI (2 octets).  This type specifies support for a set of
            components.  [Editor's note: We need to decide between Option 2 or
            Option 1.  Option 2 makes provides a better default ordering for
            frame/packet filters.</t>

                      <t hangText="Option 1"> ascending order (draft-ietf-idr-fsv2-ip-basic-02)
                        <list>
                          <t>0 - reserved, </t>
                          <t>1 - IP Basic Filter rules </t>
                          <t>2 - IP Extended Filter Rules </t>
                          <t>3 - MPLS Filter Rules </t>
                          <t>4 - L2 traffic rules</t>
                          <t>5 - SFC Traffic rules </t>
                          <t>6 - Tunneled traffic </t>
                        </list>
                      <t hangText="Option 2"> ordering by frame/packet (new)
                        <list>
      -->
                <dl spacing="compact">
                  <dt>0 -</dt>
                  <dd>Reserved</dd>

                  <dt>50 -</dt>
                  <dd>L2 Traffic fules</dd>

                  <dt>100 -</dt>
                  <dd>MPLS traffic rules</dd>

                  <dt>150 -</dt>
                  <dd>SFC Traffic rules</dd>

                  <dt>200 -</dt>
                  <dd>Tunneled traffic</dd>

                  <dt>256 -</dt>
                  <dd>IP Basic Filter Rules (bit 1 of high bit)</dd>

                  <dt>280 -</dt>
                  <dd>IP Extended Filter Rules</dd>
                </dl>
              </t>
            </li>

            <li>FSv2 Filter Component Length: A 16-bit unsigned integer in
            network byte order containing the length of the FSv2 Filter
            Components Value field.</li>

            <li>FSv2 Filter Component Value: Each FSv2 filter type will define
            one or more FSv2 filter-type-specific filter components.  See each
            FSv2 filter-type's specification for a component's definition.</li>
          </ul>
        </t>

        <t>FSv2 implementations MUST pass valid filter TLVs even if the
        implementation does not support these installation of these a particular
        type of filter rules.</t>

        <t>This specification only defines operation of the IP Basic Filter Rules
        that all FSv2 must support.  </t>
	</section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="fsv2-dependencies" title="FSv2 Dependencies">
	<t>Flow Specifications are implemented using ordered terms.  The
	sorting rules for flow specification routes is intended to, by default,
	produce a reasonably ordered set of rules for common deployment
	scenarios.</t>

	<t>When the FSv2 rule ordering wouldn't accomplish the operator's
	intent when deploying FSv2, the User Order field can permit
	the operator to influence the Flow Specification installation order in a
	deployment.</t>

	<t>When set of Flow Specifications are required to implement an
	operator's intent and that set of rules has interdependencies, the
	failure to install a Flow Specification, or part of that
	specification's actions, may result in incorrect deployment.  An
	example of such a dependency is two rules covering an IP destination,
	one with a more-specific and one with a less-specific prefix
	relaionship.  As an example:

	  <ol>
	    <li>match dst=10.1.1.1/8 tcp port=25 then dscp=AF1 and permit</li>
	    <li>match dst=10.0.0.0/8 tcp port=25 then drop</li>
	  </ol>
	</t>
      
	<t>If an implementation couldn't support the DSCP action and failed to
	install the first rule, SMTP traffic to the host 10.1.1.1 would fail to
	be delivered due to the second rule's drop action.  In other words,
	these two entries have a dependency.</t>

	<t>When an implementation is unable to install a Flow Specification for
	some reason, that Flow Specification is locally "invalid".  In many
	circumstances, Flow Specifications that do not have dependencies may be
	installed on a best-effort basis by an implementation.  However, in
	the case of dependent rules, installing some rules selectively but
	not others can be problematic.</t>
      
	<t>FSv2 defines for each FSv2 NLRI a Dependent Filters Chain (DFC).
	When the value of DFC is zero (0), no special consideration is given
	for dependencies.  When the value of DFC is non-zero, when a rule is
	locally considered invalid, all rules sharing the same DFC value are
	also considered invalid, and not installed.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Ordering of TLVs within the FSv2 NLRI">
	<t>For NLRI canonicalization purposes, and also to ease processing,
	all TLVs within the FSv2 NLRI <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ordered in
	a strictly increasing fashion.  FSv2 filter types and FSv2
	filter-type-specific component types for a given component
	<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> occur more than once.</t>

	<t>See <xref target="error-handling-and-validation"/> for further
	details.</t>
      </section>

      <!-- XXX JMH - this section should move elsewhere as well as being expanded -->
      <section title="Partial Deployments">
	<t>Partial deployments can occur for two reasons:
	  <list style="symbols">
	    <t>Only a portion of the nodes in a network with FSv2 support
	    installing new FSv2 Filter types with new FSv2 components. Other
	    nodes (such as RRs), check the syntax, but do not handle the
	    semantic meaning.</t>

	    <t>During upgrades, a portion of the nodes know about a new Filter
	    type with the components, but other nodes do not.</t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	<t>Editor: Are there others? </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="FSv2 IP Basic Filters (Filter Family Type TBD)">
      <t>FSv2 IP Basic filters provide the same functionality as those
      specified in FSv1 RFCs <xref target="RFC8955"/> and
      <xref target="RFC8956"/>.  The format of those components has been
      preserved for ease of implementation.</t>

      <t>The FSv2 IP Basic filter has been assigned a FSv2 Filter Type value of
      TBD.</t>

      <t>FSv2 IP Basic Filter component types are numbered differently from
      those in FSv1.  FSv2 components have been numbered with gaps to permit
      future FSv2 IP Basic filter components to be added in between currently
      specified IP Basic components.  This permits a natural default sort
      order for those new components in implementations.</t>

      <section title="Operators">
	<t>Most of the components described below make use of comparison
	operators. These operators were originally defined in
	<xref target="RFC8955" section="4.2.1"/>. They are repeated here for
	document clarity.</t>

	<t>The operators are encoded as a single octet.</t>

        <section title="Numeric Operator (numeric_op)" anchor="numeric-op">
          <t>This operator is encoded as shown in Figure 3-3.
            <figure title="Numeric Operator (numeric_op)">
            <artwork>
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| e | a |  len  | 0 |lt |gt |eq |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
            </artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>

          <dl>
            <dt>e (end-of-list bit): </dt>
            <dd>Set in the last {op, value} pair in the list</dd>

            <dt>a (AND bit):</dt>
            <dd> If unset, the result of the previous {op, value} pair is
            logically ORed with the current one.  If set, the operation is a
            logical AND.  In the first operator octet of a sequence, it MUST be
            encoded as unset and MUST be treated as always unset on decoding.
            The AND operator has higher priority than OR for the purposes of
            evaluating logical expressions.</dd>

            <dt>len (length): </dt>
            <dd>The length of the value field for this operator given as (1
            &lt;&lt; len).  This encodes 1 (len=00), 2 (len=01), 4 (len=10), and
            8 (len=11) octets.</dd>

            <dt>0</dt>
            <dd>MUST be set to 0 on NLRI encoding and MUST be ignored during decoding</dd>

            <dt>lt</dt>
            <dd>less-than comparison between data and value</dd>

            <dt>gt:</dt>
            <dd>greater-than comparison between data and value</dd>

            <dt>eq:</dt>
            <dd>equality between data and value</dd>
          </dl>

          <t> The bits lt, gt, and eq can be combined to produce common
          relational operators, such as "less or equal", "greater or equal", and
          "not equal to", as shown in Table 3-1.</t>

          <t>
            <figure title="Comparison Operation Combinations">
            <artwork>
+====+====+====+==================================+
| lt | gt | eq | Resulting operation              |
+====+====+====+==================================+
| 0  | 0  | 0  | false (independent of the value) |
+----+----+----+----------------------------------+
| 0  | 0  | 1  | == (equal)                       |
+----+----+----+----------------------------------+
| 0  | 1  | 0  | &gt; (greater than)                 |
+----+----+----+----------------------------------+
| 0  | 1  | 1  | &lt;= (greater than or equal)       |
+----+----+----+----------------------------------+
| 1  | 0  | 0  | &lt; (less than)                    |
+----+----+----+----------------------------------+
| 1  | 0  | 1  | &lt;= (less than or equal)          |
+----+----+----+----------------------------------+
| 1  | 1  | 0  | != (not equal value)             |
+----+----+----+----------------------------------+
| 1  | 1  | 1  | true (independent of the value)  |
+----+----+----+----------------------------------+
            </artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Bitmask Operator (bitmask_op)" anchor="bitmask-op">
          <t>This operator is encoded as shown in Figure 3-4.
            <figure title="Bitmask Operator (bitmask_op)">
            <artwork>
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| e | a |  len  | 0 | 0 |not| m |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
          </artwork>
          </figure>

          Where:</t>

          <dl>
            <dt>e, a, len (end-of-list bit, AND bit, and length field):</dt>
            <dd>Most significant nibble; defined in the Numeric Operator format
            in section 3-x.</dd>

            <dt>not (NOT bit):</dt>
            <dd>If set, logical negation of operation.</dd>

            <dt>m (Match bit):</dt>
            <dd>If set, this is a bitwise match operation defined as
            "(data AND value) == value"; if unset, (data AND value) evaluates to
            TRUE if any of the bits in the value mask are set in the data.</dd>

            <dt>0 (all 0 bits):</dt>
            <dd> MUST be set to 0 on NLRI encoding and MUST be ignored during
            decoding</dd>

          </dl>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="FSv2 IP Basic Filter Components">
	<t>FSv2 IP Basic Filter Components are encoded in FSv2 Filter Component
	TLVs as described in <xref target="fsv2-filter-components"/>.</t>

	<t>The list of valid Basic IP types, covering the functionality defined
	in <xref target="RFC8955"/> and <xref target="RFC8956"/> are documented
	below. Additional IP filters are documented in defined in
	<xref target="I-D.hares-idr-fsv2-more-ip-filters"/>.</t>

	<table align="left">
	  <name>FSv2 IP Basic Components</name>
	  <thead>
	    <tr>
	      <th>Type</th>
	      <th>Definition</th>
	    </tr>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <tr><td>0</td><td>Reserved</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>10</td><td>IP Destination Prefix</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>20</td><td>IP Source Prefix</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>30</td><td>IPv4 Protocol / IPv6 Upper Layer Protocol</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>40</td><td>Port</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>50</td><td>Destination Port</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>60</td><td>Source Port</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>70</td><td>ICMPv4 Type / ICMPv6 Type</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>80</td><td>ICMPv4 Code / ICPv6 Code</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>90</td><td>TCP Flags</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>100</td><td>Packet Length</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>110</td><td>DSCP</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>120</td><td>Fragment</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>130</td><td>Flow Label</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>4095</td><td>Reserved</td></tr>
	  </tbody>
	</table>
      </section>

      <section title="FSv2 Flow Specification Order of IP Basic Components">
	<t>For Flow Specification ordering purposes, IP Basic Filter components
	are ordered similar the FSv1 comparison rules documented in
	<xref target="RFC8955" section="5.1"/>.</t>

	<t>The relative order of two Flow Specificationss with IP Basic filter
	family components is determined by comparing their respective
	family-specific components. The algorithm starts by comparing the lowest component type
	value of the Flow Specifications. If the types differ, the Flow
	Specification with lowest numeric type value has higher precedence (and
	thus will match before) than the Flow Specification that doesn't
	contain that component type. If the component types are the same, then
	a type-specific comparison is performed (see below). If the types are
	equal, the algorithm continues with the next component.</t>

	<t>For IP prefix values (IP destination or source prefix), if one of the
	two prefixes to compare is a more specific prefix of the other, the
	more specific prefix has higher precedence. Otherwise, the one with the
	lowest IP value has higher precedence.</t>

	<t>For all other component types, unless otherwise specified, the
	comparison is performed by comparing the component data as a binary
	string using the memcmp() function as defined by [ISO_IEC_9899]. For
	strings with equal lengths, the lowest string (memcmp) has higher
	precedence. For strings of different lengths, the common prefix is
	compared. If the common prefix is not equal, the string with the lowest
	prefix has higher precedence. If the common prefix is equal, the
	longest string is considered to have higher precedence than the shorter
	one.</t>
      <!-- XXX JMH - the rules above are NOT generic and implementations with a mix of an old and a new FS component/family need to be able to select things consistently! -->
      </section>

      <section title="FSv2 Components for IP Basic TLVs">
        <section title="IP Destination Prefix (component type = 10)">
	  <section title="IPv4 Destination Prefix (AFI=1)">
	    <t><tt>Encoding: &lt;prefix length (1 octet), prefix (variable)&gt;</tt></t>

	    <t>Defines the IPv4 destination prefix to match.</t>

	    <dl spacing="compact">
	      <dt><strong>prefix length:</strong></dt><dd>Length of the prefix in bits.</dd>
	      <dt><strong>prefix:</strong></dt><dd>IPv4 Prefix encoded using <xref target="RFC4271"/> NLRI format.</dd>
	    </dl>
	  </section>
	  <section title="IPv6 Destination Prefix (AFI=2)" anchor="ipv6-dst-prefix">
	    <t><tt>Encoding: &lt;length (1 octet), offset (1 octet), pattern (variable), padding (variable)&gt;</tt></t>

	    <t>This defines the IPv6 destination prefix to match. The offset
	    has been defined to allow for flexible matching to portions of an
	    IPv6 address where one is required to skip over the first N bits of
	    the address. (These bits skipped are often indicated as "don't
	    care" bits.) This can be especially useful where part of the IPv6
	    address consists of an embedded IPv4 address, and matching needs to
	    happen only on the embedded IPv4 address. The encoded pattern
	    contains enough octets for the bits used in matching (length minus
	    offset bits).</t>

	    <dl spacing="compact">
              <dt><strong>length:</strong></dt>
	      <dd>This indicates the N-th most significant bit in the address where bitwise pattern matching stops.</dd>
	      <dt><strong>offset:</strong></dt>
	      <dd>This indicates the number of most significant address bits to skip before bitwise pattern matching starts.</dd>
	      <dt><strong>pattern:</strong></dt>
	      <dd>This contains the matching pattern. The length of the pattern
	      is defined by the number of bits needed for pattern matching
	      (length minus offset).</dd>
	      <dt><strong>padding:</strong></dt>
	      <dd>This contains the minimum number of bits required to pad the
	      component to an octet boundary. Padding bits MUST be 0 on
	      encoding and MUST be ignored on decoding.</dd>
	    </dl>

	    <t>If length = 0 and offset = 0, this component matches every
	    address; otherwise, length MUST be in the range offset &lt; length &lt;
	    129 or the component is malformed.</t>

	    <t>Note: This Flow Specification component can be represented by
	    the notation ipv6address/length if offset is 0 or
	    ipv6address/offset-length. The ipv6address in this notation is the
	    textual IPv6 representation of the pattern shifted to the right by
	    the number of offset bits.</t>
	  </section>
        </section>

        <section title="IP Source Prefix (type = 20)">
	  <section title="IPv4 Source Prefix (AFI=1)">
	    <t><tt>Encoding: &lt;prefix length (1 octet), prefix (variable)&gt;</tt></t>

	    <t>Defines the IPv4 source prefix to match.</t>

	    <dl spacing="compact">
	      <dt><strong>prefix length:</strong></dt><dd>Length of the prefix in bits.</dd>
	      <dt><strong>prefix:</strong></dt><dd>IPv4 Prefix encoded using <xref target="RFC4271"/> NLRI format.</dd>
	    </dl>
	  </section>

	  <section title="IPv6 Source Prefix (AFI=2)">
	    <t><tt>Encoding: &lt;length (1 octet), offset (1 octet), pattern (variable), padding (variable)&gt;</tt></t>

	    <t>This defines the source prefix to match. The length, offset, pattern, and padding are the same as in <xref target="ipv6-dst-prefix"/>.</t>
	  </section>
        </section>

        <section title="IP Protocol/IPv6 Upper Layer Protocol (type = 30)">
	  <t><tt>Encoding: &lt;[numeric_op, value]+&gt;</tt></t>

	  <section title="IPv4 Protocol (AFI=1)">
	    <t>Contains a list of <tt>{numeric_op, value}</tt> pairs that are
	    used to match the IP protocol value octet in IPv4 packet header
	    <xref target="RFC0791" section="3.1"/>.</t>

	    <t>This component uses the Numeric Operator (numeric_op) described
	    in <xref target="numeric-op"/>. Type 30 component values SHOULD be
	    encoded as single octet (numeric_op len=00).</t>
	  </section>

	  <section title="IPv6 Upper Layer Protocol (AFI=2)">
	    <t>This contains a list of <tt>{numeric_op, value}</tt> pairs that
	    are used to match the first Next Header value octet in IPv6 packets
	    that is not an extension header and thus indicates that the next
	    item in the packet is the corresponding upper-layer header
	    (see <xref target="RFC8200" section="4"/> Section 4).</t>

	    <t>This component uses the Numeric Operator (numeric_op) described
	    in <xref target="numeric-op"/>. Type 30 component values SHOULD be
	    encoded as a single octet (numeric_op len=00).</t>

	    <t>Note: While IPv6 allows for more than one Next Header field in
	    the packet, the main goal of the Type 30 Flow Specification
	    component is to match on the first upper-layer IP protocol value.
	    Therefore, the definition is limited to match only on this specific
	    Next Header field in the packet.</t>
	  </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Port (type = 40)" anchor="port">
	  <t><tt>Encoding: &lt;[numeric_op, value]+&gt;</tt></t>

	  <t>Defines a list of <tt>{numeric_op, value}</tt> pairs that match
	  source OR destination TCP/UDP ports (see <xref target="RFC0793"
	  section="3.1"/> and the "Format" section of <xref
	  target="RFC0768"/>). This component matches if either the destination
	  port OR the source port of an IP packet matches the value.</t>

	  <t>This component uses the Numeric Operator (numeric_op) described in
	  <xref target="numeric-op"/>. Type 40 component values SHOULD be
	  encoded as 1- or 2-octet quantities (numeric_op len=00 or
	  len=01).</t>

	  <t>In case of the presence of the port (destination-port (<xref
	  target="dst-port"/>), source-port (<xref target="src-port"/>)
	  component, only TCP or UDP packets can match the entire Flow
	  Specification. The port component, if present, never matches when the
	  packet's IP protocol value is not 6 (TCP) or 17 (UDP), if the packet
	  is fragmented and this is not the first fragment, or if the system is
	  unable to locate the transport header. Different implementations may
	  or may not be able to decode the transport header in the presence of
	  IP options or Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP) NULL
	  <xref target="RFC4303"/> encryption.</t>

          <t>Note: This component only matches the first upper layer protocol
          value in IPv6.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Destination Port (type = 50)" anchor="dst-port">
	  <t><tt>Encoding: &lt;[numeric_op, value]+&gt;</tt></t>

	  <t>Defines a list of <tt>{numeric_op, value}</tt> pairs used to match
	  the destination port of a TCP or UDP packet (see also
	  <xref target="RFC0793" section="3.1"/> and the "Format" section of
	  <xref target="RFC0768"/>.</t>

	  <t>This component uses the Numeric Operator (numeric_op) described in
	  <xref target="numeric-op"/>. Type 50 component values SHOULD be
	  encoded as 1- or 2-octet quantities (numeric_op len=00 or
	  len=01).</t>

	  <t>The last paragraph of <xref target="port"/> also applies to this
	  component.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Source Port (type = 60)" anchor="src-port">
	  <t><tt>Encoding: &lt;[numeric_op, value]+&gt;</tt></t>

	  <t>Defines a list of <tt>{numeric_op, value}</tt> pairs used to match
	  the source port of a TCP or UDP packet (see also
	  <xref target="RFC0793" section="3.1"/> and the "Format" section of
	  <xref target="RFC0768"/>.</t>

	  <t>This component uses the Numeric Operator (numeric_op) described in
	  <xref target="numeric-op"/>. Type 60 component values SHOULD be
	  encoded as 1- or 2-octet quantities (numeric_op len=00 or
	  len=01).</t>

	  <t>The last paragraph of <xref target="port"/> also applies to this
	  component.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="ICMP Type (type = 70)">
	  <t><tt>Encoding: &lt;[numeric_op, value]+&gt;</tt></t>

	  <t>Defines a list of <tt>{numeric_op, value}</tt> pairs used to match
	  the type field of an ICMP packet (see also the "Message Formats"
	  section of <xref target="RFC0792"/>).</t>

	  <t>This component uses the Numeric Operator (numeric_op) described in
	  <xref target="numeric-op"/>. Type 70 component values SHOULD be
	  encoded as single octet (numeric_op len=00).</t>

	  <section title="ICMP IPv4 Type (AFI=1)">
	    <t>In case of the presence of the ICMP type component, only ICMP
	    packets can match the entire Flow Specification. The ICMP type
	    component, if present, never matches when the packet's IP protocol
	    value is not 1 (ICMP), if the packet is fragmented and this is not
	    the first fragment, or if the system is unable to locate the
	    transport header. Different implementations may or may not be able
	    to decode the transport header in the presence of IP options or
	    Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP) NULL <xref target="RFC4303"/>
	    encryption.</t>
	  </section>

	  <section title="ICMP IPv6 Type (AFI=2)">
	    <t>In case of the presence of the ICMPv6 type component, only
	    ICMPv6 packets can match the entire Flow Specification. The ICMPv6
	    type component, if present, never matches when the packet's
	    upper-layer IP protocol value is not 58 (ICMPv6), if the packet is
	    fragmented and this is not the first fragment, or if the system is
	    unable to locate the transport header. Different implementations
	    may or may not be able to decode the transport header.</t>
	  </section>
        </section>

        <section title="ICMP Code (type = 80)">
	  <t><tt>Encoding: &lt;[numeric_op, value]+&gt;</tt></t>

	  <section title="ICMP Code IPv4 Type (AFI=1)">
	    <t>Defines a list of <tt>{numeric_op, value}</tt> pairs used to
	    match the code field of an ICMP packet (see also the "Message
	    Formats" section of <xref target="RFC0792"/>).</t>

	    <t>This component uses the Numeric Operator (numeric_op) described
	    in <xref target="numeric-op"/>. Type 80 component values SHOULD be
	    encoded as single octet (numeric_op len=00).</t>

	    <t>In case of the presence of the ICMP code component, only ICMP
	    packets can match the entire Flow Specification. The ICMP code
	    component, if present, never matches when the packet's IP protocol
	    value is not 1 (ICMP), if the packet is fragmented and this is not
	    the first fragment, or if the system is unable to locate the
	    transport header. Different implementations may or may not be able
	    to decode the transport header in the presence of IP options or
	    Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP) NULL <xref target="RFC4303"/>
	    encryption.</t>
	  </section>

	  <section title="ICMP Code IPv6 Type (AFI=2)">
	    <t>This defines a list of {numeric_op, value} pairs used to match
	    the code field of an ICMPv6 packet (see also
	    <xref target="RFC4443" section="2.1"/>).</t>

	    <t>This component uses the Numeric Operator (numeric_op) described
	    in <xref target="numeric-op"/>. Type 80 component values SHOULD be
	    encoded as a single octet (numeric_op len=00).</t>

	    <t>In case of the presence of the ICMPv6 code component, only
	    ICMPv6 packets can match the entire Flow Specification. The ICMPv6
	    code component, if present, never matches when the packet's
	    upper-layer IP protocol value is not 58 (ICMPv6), if the packet is
	    fragmented and this is not the first fragment, or if the system is
	    unable to locate the transport header. Different implementations
	    may or may not be able to decode the transport header.</t>
	  </section>
        </section>

        <section title="TCP Flags (type = 90)" >
	  <t><tt>Encoding: &lt;[bitmask_op, bitmask]+&gt;</tt></t>

	  <t>Defines a list of <tt>{bitmask_op, bitmask}</tt> pairs used to
	  match TCP control bits (see also
	  <xref target="RFC0793" section="3.1"/>).</t>

	  <t>This component uses the Bitmask Operator (bitmask_op) described in
	  <xref target="bitmask-op"/>. Type 90 component bitmasks MUST be
	  encoded as 1- or 2-octet bitmask (bitmask_op len=00 or len=01).</t>

	  <t>When a single octet (bitmask_op len=00) is specified, it matches
	  octet 14 of the TCP header (see also
	  <xref target="RFC0793" section="3.1"/>), which contains the TCP
	  control bits. When a 2-octet (bitmask_op len=01) encoding is used, it
	  matches octets 13 and 14 of the TCP header with the data offset
	  (leftmost 4 bits) always treated as 0.</t>

	  <t>In case of the presence of the TCP flags component, only TCP
	  packets can match the entire Flow Specification. The TCP flags
	  component, if present, never matches when the packet's IP protocol
	  value is not 6 (TCP), if the packet is fragmented and this is not the
	  first fragment, or if the system is unable to locate the transport
	  header. Different implementations may or may not be able to decode
	  the transport header in the presence of IP options or Encapsulating
	  Security Payload (ESP) NULL <xref target="RFC4303"/> encryption.</t>

	  <!-- XXX JMH the intention here was to be more restrictive?
          <t>Note: a 2 octets bitmask match is always used for TCP-Flags </t>
	  -->
        </section>

        <section title="Packet length (type = 100)">
	  <t><tt>Encoding: &lt;[numeric_op, value]+&gt;</tt></t>

	  <t>Defines a list of <tt>{numeric_op, value}</tt> pairs used to match
	  on the total IP packet length (excluding Layer 2 but including IP
	  header).</t>

	  <t>This component uses the Numeric Operator (numeric_op) described in
	  <xref target="numeric-op"/>. Type 100 component values SHOULD be
	  encoded as 1- or 2-octet quantities (numeric_op len=00 or
	  len=01).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="DSCP (Differentiaed Services Code Point)(type = 110)">
	  <t><tt>Encoding: &lt;[numeric_op, value]+&gt;</tt></t>

	  <t>Defines a list of <tt>{numeric_op, value}</tt> pairs used to match
	  the 6-bit DSCP field (see also <xref target="RFC2474"/>).</t>

	  <t>This component uses the Numeric Operator (numeric_op) described in
	  <xref target="numeric-op"/>. Type 110 component values MUST be
	  encoded as single octet (numeric_op len=00).</t>

	  <t>The six least significant bits contain the DSCP value. All other
	  bits SHOULD be treated as 0.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Fragment (type = 120)">
	  <t><tt>Encoding: &lt;[bitmask_op, bitmask]+&gt;</tt></t>

	  <t>Defines a list of <tt>{bitmask_op, bitmask}</tt> pairs used to
	  match specific IP fragments.</t>

	  <t>This component uses the Bitmask Operator (bitmask_op) described in
	  <xref target="bitmask-op"/>. Type 120 component bitmask MUST be
	  encoded as single octet bitmask (bitmask_op len=00).</t>

	  <section title="IPv4 Fragment (AFI=1)">
	    <t>
	      <figure title="IPv4 Fragment Bitmask Operand">
	      <artwork>
    0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
  +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
  | 0 | 0 | 0 | 0 |LF |FF |IsF|DF |
  +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
	      </artwork>
	      </figure>
	    </t>

	    <t>Bitmask values:</t>

	    <dl>
	      <dt><strong>DF (Don't Fragment):</strong></dt>
	      <dd>match if IP Header Flags Bit-1 (DF) <xref target="RFC0791"/> is 1</dd>

	      <dt><strong>IsF (Is a fragment other than the first):</strong></dt>
	      <dd>match if the <xref target="RFC0791"/> IP Header Fragment Offset is not 0</dd>

	      <dt><strong>FF (First Fragment):</strong></dt>
	      <dd>match if the <xref target="RFC0791"/> IP Header Fragment Offset is 0 AND Flags Bit-2 (MF) is 1</dd>

	      <dt><strong>LF (Last Fragment):</strong></dt>
	      <dd>match if the <xref target="RFC0791"/> IP Header Fragment Offset is not 0 AND Flags Bit-2 (MF) is 0</dd>

	      <dt><strong>0:</strong></dt>
	      <dd>MUST be set to 0 on NLRI encoding and MUST be ignored during decoding</dd>
	    </dl>
	  </section>

	  <section title="IPv6 Fragment (AFI=2)">
	    <t>
	      <figure title="IPv6 Fragment Bitmask Operand">
	      <artwork>
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 0 | 0 | 0 | 0 |LF |FF |IsF| 0 |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
	      </artwork>
	      </figure>
	    </t>

	    <t>Bitmask values:</t>

	    <dl>
	      <dt><strong>IsF:</strong></dt>
	      <dd>Is a fragment other than the first -- match if IPv6 Fragment Header (<xref target="RFC8200" section="4.5"/>) Fragment Offset is not 0</dd>

	      <dt><strong>FF:</strong></dt>
	      <dd>First fragment -- match if IPv6 Fragment Header (<xref target="RFC8200" section="4.5"/>) Fragment Offset is 0 AND M flag is 1</dd>

	      <dt><strong>LF:</strong></dt>
	      <dd>Last fragment -- match if IPv6 Fragment Header (<xref target="RFC8200" section="4.5"/>) Fragment Offset is not 0 AND M flag is 0</dd>

	      <dt><strong>0:</strong></dt>
	      <dd>MUST be set to 0 on NLRI encoding and MUST be ignored during decoding</dd>
	    </dl>
	  </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Flow Label (type = 130), AFI=2 only">
	  <t><tt>Encoding: &lt;[numeric_op, value]+&gt;</tt></t>

	  <t>This contains a list of {numeric_op, value} pairs that are used to
	  match the 20-bit Flow Label IPv6 header field
	  (<xref target="RFC8200" section="3"/>).</t>

	  <t>This component uses the Numeric Operator (numeric_op) described in
	  <xref target="numeric-op"/>. Type 130 component values SHOULD be
	  encoded as 4-octet quantities (numeric_op len=10).</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <!-- XXX JMH We need to normalize the short form of flow specifications.
      flowspec? Flow Spec? -->
      <section title="FSv2 Traffic Filtering Actions for FSv2 IP Basic ">
	<t>Traffic matching a flow specification filter may have selected
	<em>traffic actions</em> applied to it that have various impacts on the
	matched traffic. FSv2 IP Basic allows flow specification actions to be
	attached to flow specification routes using BGP Extended Communities
	(FSv2-EC) encoded using the Extended Community formats
	<xref target="RFC4360"/> or in the IPv6 Address Specific Extended
	Community format <xref target="RFC5701"/>.</t>

	<t><xref target="fs-interactions"/> describes the interaction between
	FS-EC action, and categories of actions.  <xref target="fsv2-actions"/>
	describes the existing FS-EC action formats.  <xref target="fsv2-ec-aco"/>
	defines an optional FS-EC to pass information ordering of categories
	(user/this standard) and failure action (stop or best effort).</t>

	<section title="Categories of FSv2 Actions and their Interactions" anchor="fs-interactions">

	  <t>FSv2-EC actions fall into the following categories:

	    <ul>
	      <li>Further constraint of the match criteria for the traffic in
	      addition to that which is encoded in the NLRI.</li>

	      <li>Apply traffic shaping mechanisms, such as bps/pps rate
	      limiters.</li>

	      <li>Change IP packet properties, such as DSCP.</li>

	      <li>Redirect (change the forwarding) of the traffic.  Examples
	      include redirecting to VPN VRFs, or forwarding to tunneled
	      destinations.</li>

	      <li>Flag the traffic for sampling.</li>

	      <li>Terminate the evaluation of further flow specification
	      matches in the forwarding plane.</li>
	    </ul>
	  </t>

	  <t>When multiple actions from a given FSv2-EC category are present in
	  a FSv2 route, these actions may <em>conflict</em>. Conflicting
	  actions result in ambiguity as to what traffic action behavior is
	  applied to traffic matching the flow specification.</t>

	  <t>FSv2 actions passed in a BGP Community Container Attribute can
	  provide ordering of actions, dependencies, or signal which actions are
	  valid within a category (see
	  <xref target="I-D.hares-idr-fsv2-more-ip-actions"/>).
	  However, these features are beyond the Basic FSv2 for IP forwarding
	  and are out of scope for this specification.</t>
	</section>

        <section title="FSv2 Extended Community Actions" anchor="fsv2-actions">
	  <t>FSv2 IP Basic uses FSv1 actions and these are referenced in
	  <xref target="fsv2-ec-rfc4360"/> and <xref target="fsv2-ec-rfc5701"/>.</t>

	  <t>One additional, optional, FSv2 specific FS-EC: the Action Chain
	  Ordering (ACO) Extended Community (ACO-EC), is defined in
	  <xref target="fsv2-ec-aco"/>.  ACO-EC can carry defaults currently
	  only available by configuration in FSv1.</t>

          <section title="Existing Flow Specification Action Extended Communities" anchor="fsv2-ec-rfc4360">
	    <t>FSv1 defines a set of <xref target="RFC4360"/> encoded extended
	    communities implementing actions also applicable to FSv2 IP Basic
	    match types.  They are:</t>

	    <table align="left">
	      <name>FSv1 Extended Communities Used by FSv2</name>
	      <thead>
		<tr>
		  <th>Type/Sub-Type</th>
		  <th>Description</th>
		  <th>Short-ID</th>
		  <th>Reference</th>
		</tr>
	      </thead>
	      <tbody>
		<tr>
		  <td>0x01/0x0c</td>
		  <td>Redirect to IP</td>
		  <td>RD-IP</td>
		  <td><xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-redirect-ip"/></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
		  <td>0x07/0x02</td>
		  <td>Match Interface set</td>
		  <td>TA-IS</td>
		  <td><xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-interfaceset"/></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
		  <td>0x09/0xxx</td>
		  <td>Redirect to Indirection ID</td>
		  <td>RD-IID</td>
		  <td><xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-path-redirect"/></td>
		</tr>
		<!-- XXX JMH - these SFC code points need review to see if they belong here. -->
		<tr>
		  <td>0x0b/0x00</td>
		  <td>SFC Reserved</td>
		  <td>SFC-R</td>
		  <td><xref target="RFC9015"/></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
		  <td>0x0b/0x01</td>
		  <td>SFVC SFIR POOL Identifier</td>
		  <td>SFIR-PI</td>
		  <td><xref target="RFC9015"/></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
		  <td>0x0b/0x02</td>
		  <td>SFC MPLS label stack Swapping or stacking labels</td>
		  <td>SFC-MPLS</td>
		  <td><xref target="RFC9015"/></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
		  <td>0x80/0x06</td>
		  <td>Traffic rate limit by bytes</td>
		  <td>TR-BPS</td>
		  <td><xref target="RFC8955"/></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
		  <td>0x80/0x07</td>
		  <td>Traffic Action (sample, terminal)</td>
		  <td>TA</td>
		  <td><xref target="RFC8955"/></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
		  <td>0x80/0x08</td>
		  <td>Redirection to VRF (2-octet AS form)</td>
		  <td>RD-VRF-AS2</td>
		  <td><xref target="RFC8955"/></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
		  <td>0x80/0x09</td>
		  <td>Traffic mark DSCP</td>
		  <td>TM-DSCP</td>
		  <td><xref target="RFC8955"/></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
		  <td>0x80/0x0C</td>
		  <td>Traffic rate limit by packets</td>
		  <td>TR-BPS</td>
		  <td><xref target="RFC8955"/></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
		  <td>0x81/0x08</td>
		  <td>Redirect to VPN (IPv4 form)</td>
		  <td>RD-VRF-IPv4</td>
		  <td><xref target="RFC8955"/></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
		  <td>0x81/0x08</td>
		  <td>Redirect to VPN (4-octet AS form)</td>
		  <td>RD-VRF-AS4</td>
		  <td><xref target="RFC8955"/></td>
		</tr>
	      </tbody>
	    </table>

            <t> Note the Short ID is simply a quick way for this document to
            reference a particular action.</t>

          </section>
          <section title="Existing Flow Specification Actions IPv6 Address Specific Extended Communities" anchor="fsv2-ec-rfc5701">
	    <t>FSv1 defines a set of <xref target="RFC5701"/> encoded extended
	    communities implementing actions also applicable to FSv2 IP Basic
	    match types.  They are:</t>

	    <table align="left">
	      <name>FSv1 IPv6 Address Specific Extended Communities Used by FSv2</name>
	      <thead>
		<tr>
		  <th>Type</th>
		  <th>Description</th>
		  <th>Short-ID</th>
		  <th>Reference</th>
		</tr>
	      </thead>
	      <tbody>
		<tr>
		  <td>0x000C</td>
		  <td>FS Redirect to IPv6</td>
		  <td>RD-IP6</td>
		  <td><xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-redirect-ip"/></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
		  <td>0x000D</td>
		  <td>FS Redirect to VPN by IPv6 route target</td>
		  <td>RD-VRF-IPv6</td>
		  <td><xref target="RFC8956"/></td>
		</tr>
	      </tbody>
	    </table>
          </section>
        </section>

	<section title="Failure of an FS-EC Action" >
	  <t>Devices implementing flow specification matching and traffic
	  actions may be unable, for whatever reason, to carry out the signaled
	  actions for the matched traffic.  Some examples of this inability
	  include:

	    <ul>
	      <li>The action is not implemented in the forwarding plane.</li>

	      <li>Combinations of non-conflicting actions may not be able to be
	      simultaneously executed due to limitation in the implementation's
	      forwarding plane.</li>
	    </ul>
	  </t>
<!-- XXX JMH - need to deal with *unknown* actions -->

	  <t>When FS-EC actions known to the implementation are attached to a
	  flow specification route and an action cannot be executed, there are
	  three potential options:

	    <ol type="Option %d:">
	      <li>Stop processing additional filters and (optionally) signal failure to the management process.</li>
	      <li>Continue on processing in "best effort" for the next filters.</li>
	      <li>Decide between 1 and 2 based on dependencies between filters and actions.</li>
	    </ol>
	  </t>

	  <t>Option 1 and 2 can be signaled by configuration within a Flow
	  Specification implementation.</t>

	  <t>Option 3 requires the encoding dependency lists in ordered filters
	  and ordered actions.  The FSv2 NLRI format has a field to carry
	  filter dependency information, but these functions are beyond the
	  FSv2 Basic IP functions and out of scope for this specification.</t>

	  <t>Consider an example where three FSv2-EC actions are present on the route: Set the DSCP value, request sampling of the traffic, redirect to a VRF. If the implementation is unable to set the DSCP value:

	    <ol type="Option %d">
	      <li>would be to stop processing and not do the other two actions.</li>
	      <li>would be to continue prcoessing and do the other two actions.</li>
	    </ol>
	  </t>

	  <t>Currently, for FSv1, local configuration or implementation
	  behavior determines what happens if one of the actions fails within a
	  set of multiple actions attached to a filter rule.</t>

	  <t>One option for FSv2 is to pass another FS-EC indicating what the
	  originator expects will happen upon failure of an action.</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Unknown FSv2-EC Actions">
	  <t>A flow specification implementation that understands extended
	  communities for a traffic action may not necessarily be able to
	  implement them. Another problematic case for consistent deployment of
	  flow specification within a network is understanding that an
	  implementation may be ignorant of some FSv2-ECs.</t>

	  <t>FSv2-ECs are carried in the general purpose BGP Extended Community
	  features.  The expected behavior for an implementation receiving
	  unknown Extended Communities, depending on configuration and policy,
	  will be to ignore the contents of these communities and propagate
	  them according to the transitivity rules in
	  <xref target="RFC4360"/>.</t>

	  <t>Newly defined FSv2-ECs may be unknown to the implementation,
	  typically as a result of incremental deployment newer flow
	  specification traffic actions. When a network with older
	  implementations receive such newly defined FSv2-ECs, the older
	  implementations are unable to determine that an action has been
	  requested at all. The default behavior thus becomes "best effort"
	  for executing the known FSv2-ECs.</t>

	  <t>When specifying new FSv2-ECs, operational consideration
	  <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be given to what the behavior of such ignorant
	  implementations may do to the desired traffic forwarding throughout
	  the FS deployment.</t>
	</section>

	<!-- XXX JMH - I'm a bit unclear on some of the intended details here
	for ACO.  I think the desire is "what do you do if you fail to execute
	a known action?"  The text is focusing on pairs that I don't
	understand. -->
	<section title="Action Chain Ordering FSv2-EC (ACO) (optional)" anchor="fsv2-ec-aco">
	  <t>
	    <dl>
	      <dt>Summary:</dt>
	      <dd>This optional FSv2-EC passes information on what the BGP
	      peer originating the FSv2-EC expects will happen with multiple
	      actions attached to a single filter.</dd>

		<dt>Description:</dt>
		<dd>The BGP peer originating multiple FSv2 FS-EC actions
		attached to FSv2 NLRI (filters) may attach the Action Chain
		Ordering (ACO) FS-EC to inform BGP Peers receiving the FSv2
		information how the originating pair expects action
		interactions and actions failures will be handled. Two fields
		are encoded in this FS-EC:

		<list>
		  <t>AC-interaction - What happens if two actions are
		  specified in a category, and</t>

		  <t>AC-Failure - what happens if an action with multiple
		  action set fails.</t>
		</list>
	      </dd>

	      <dt>Encoding:</dt>
	      <dd>The Generic Transitive encoding is shown in <xref target="aco-fsv2-ec"/>
	      with the field definitions below.</dd>
	    </dl>
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    <figure title="Action Chain Ordering FSv2-EC" anchor="aco-fsv2-ec">
	    <artwork>
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type high    |  Type low     |AC-interaction |  AC-Failure   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|        Reserved  (4 octets)                                   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	    </artwork>
	    </figure>
	  </t>

	  <t>where:
	    <dl>
	      <dt><strong>Type high:</strong></dt>
	      <dd> This 1 octet field has a value of 0x80 For the Generic
	      Transitive EC.</dd>

	      <dt><strong>Type low:</strong></dt>
	      <dd> This one octet field identifies the ACO-Action.  The value
	      is TBD4.</dd>

	      <dt><strong>AC-interaction:</strong></dt>
	      <dd>This field indicates whether the FS-EC category order is
	      the pre-defined order or an implementation specific order.

		<ul>
		  <li>0 (default): Do not install actions with two actions per
		  category.</li>

		  <li>1 (local config): Allow under local configuration.</li>
		</ul>
	      </dd>

	      <dt><strong>AC-failure:</strong></dt>
	      <dd>1 octet byte that determines the action on failure.
	      Actions may succeed or fail and an Action chain must deal with
	      it.  The default value stored for an action chain that does not
	      have this action chain is "stop on failure".  AC-Failure
	      types are:

		<ul>
		  <li>0x00: Stop on failure of an action.</li>
		  <li>0x01: Continue on failure of an action.</li>
		</ul>
	      </dd>

	      <dt><strong>Reserved:</strong></dt>
	      <dd>Reserved for future use.  Must be set to all zeros, and
	      ignored upon reception.</dd>
	    </dl>
	  </t>
	</section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="fsv2-validation-and-ordering" title="Validation and Ordering of NLRI">
      <section title="Validation of FSv2 NLRI ">
        <t>The validation of FSv2 NLRI adheres to the combination of rules for
        general BGP FSv1 NLRI found in <xref target="RFC8955"></xref>, <xref
        target="RFC8956"></xref>, <xref target="RFC9117"></xref>.  These FSv1
        rules are sufficient for FSv2 for IP traffic.</t>

        <t> Specific additions have been defined for IP Filters used for
        guiding IP traffic into Service Function Service Function Pathways SFC
        NLRI in <xref target="RFC9015"></xref>, or validation of L2VPN FS NLRI
        (see <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-l2vpn"></xref>).  These
        additions are not required for the FSv2 for IP Basic functions.
        Therefore, FSv2 NLRI validation for Basic IP uses the same rules as
        FSv1.</t>

        <t>To provide clarity, the full validation process for flow
        specification routes (FSv1 or FSv2) for all AFI/SAFIs is described
        below in section x.x rather than simply referring to the relevant
        portions of these RFCs.  Validation only occurs after BGP UPDATE
        message reception and the FSv2 NLRI and the path attributes relating to
        FSv2 (Extended community and Wide Community) have been determined to be
        well-formed.  Any MALFORMED FSv2 NRLI is handled as a "session reset"
        <xref target="RFC7606"></xref>.</t>

        <section title="Validation of FS NLRI (FSv1 or FSv2)">
          <t> Flow specifications received from a BGP peer that are accepted in
          the respective Adj-RIB-In are used as input to the route selection
          process.  Although the forwarding attributes of the two routes for
          tbe same prefix may be the same, BGP is still required to perform its
          path selection algorithm in order to select the correct set of
          attributes to advertise.</t>

          <t>The first step of the BGP Route selection procedure (section 9.1.2
          of <xref target="RFC4271"></xref> is to exclude from the selection
          procedure routes that are considered unfeasible. In the context of IP
          routing information, this is used to validate that the NEXT_HOP
          Attribute of a given route is resolvable.</t>

          <t>The concept can be extended in the case of the Flow Specification
          NLRI to allow other validation procedures.</t>

          <t>The FSv2 validation process validates the FSv2 NLRI with following
          unicast routes received over the same AFI (1 or 2) but different
          SAFIs:

            <dl>
              <dt>FSv2 received over SAFI=TBD1</dt>
              <dd> FSv1 received over SAFI=133 are be validated against SAFI=1.
              Similarly, FSv2 routes received over SAFI=TBD1 will be validated
              against SAFI=1.</dd>

              <dt>FSv2 received over SAFI=TBD2</dt>
              <dd>FSv1 received over SAFI=134 are validated against SAFI=128,
              and FSv2 received over SAFI=TBD2 will be validated against
              SAFI=128.</dd>

              <dt>FSv2 received with AFI = 31</dt>
              <dd> The FSV2 routes received with (AFI=31, SAFI=TBD1) will be
              validated against SAFI=1.  The FSv2 received with (AFI=31,
              SAFI=TBD2) will be validated against SAFI=128.</dd>

              <dt>FSv2 L2 routes passed in (AFI=6, SAFI=TBD1) and L2VPN routes
              passed in (AFI=25, SAFI=TBD2).</dt>
              <dd>
                <dl>
                  <dt>FSv2 L2 routes -</dt>
                  <dd> validate (AFI=6, SAFI=TBD1) against (AFI=1, SAFI=1).</dd>

                  <dt>FSv2 L2VPN routes -</dt>
                  <dd> validate (AFI=256, SAFI=TBD2) against (AFI=1, SAFI=128></dd>

                  <dt>This is similar to FSv1. -</dt>
                  <dd> The FSv1 L2 validated L2 routes passed in (AFI=6,
                  SAFI=133) against (AFI=1, SAFI=1) and the L2VPN routes
                  (AFI=25, SAFI=134) are validated against (AFI=1, SAFI=128).</dd>
                </dl>
              </dd>
            </dl>
          </t>

          <t>In the absence of explicit configuration, a Flow specification
          NLRI (FSv1 or FSv2) MUST be validated such that it is considered
          feasible if and only if all of the conditions are true:

            <list>
              <t>a) A destination prefix component is embedded in the Flow
              Specification,</t>
              <t>b) One of the following conditions holds true:

                <list>
                  <t>1. The originator of the Flow Specification matches the
                  originator of the best-match unicast route for the destination
                  prefix embedded in the flow specification (this is the unicast
                  route with the longest possible prefix length covering the
                  destination prefix embedded in the flow specification).</t>

                  <t>2. The AS_PATH attribute of the flow specification is empty
                  or contains only an AS_CONFED_SEQUENCE segment
                  <xref target="RFC5065"></xref>.

                    <list>
                      <t>2a.This condition should be enabled by default.</t>
                      <t>2b.This condition may be disabled by explicit
                      configuration on a BGP Speaker,</t>
                      <t>2c.As an extension to this rule, a given non-empty
                      AS_PATH (besides AS_CONFED_SEQUENCE segments) MAY be
                      permitted by policy].</t>
                    </list>
                  </t>
                </list>
              </t>

              <t>c) There are no "more-specific" unicast routes when compared
              with the flow destination prefix that have been received from a
              different neighbor AS than the best-match unicast route, which
              has been determined in rule b.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>However, part of rule a may be relaxed by explicit configuration,
          permitting Flow Specifications that include no destination prefix
          component.  If such is the case, rules b and c are moot and MUST be
          disregarded.</t>

          <t>By "originator" of a BGP route, we mean either the address of the
          originator in the ORIGINATOR_ID Attribute
          <xref target="RFC4456"></xref> or the source address of the BGP peer,
          if this path attribute is not present.</t>

          <t>A BGP implementation MUST enforce that the AS in the left-most
          position of the AS_PATH attribute of a Flow Specification Route (FSv1
          or FSv2) received via the Exterior Border Gateway Protocol (eBGP)
          matches the AS in the left-most position of the AS_PATH attribute of
          the best-match unicast route for the destination prefix embedded in
          the Flow Specification (FSv1 or FSv2) NLRI.</t>

          <t>The best-match unicast route may change over time independently of
          the Flow Specification NLRI (FSv1 or FSv2). Therefore, a revalidation
          of the Flow Specification MUST be performed whenever unicast routes
          change.  Revalidation is defined as retesting rules a to c as
          described above.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Validation of Flow Specification Actions for FSv2 for IP Basic">
          <t>A match on a Flow Specification (FS) filters is linked to one or
          more FS action set by an Extended Communities (FS-EC) for FSv2 for IP
          Basic functions.</t>

          <t>Validation of FS-EC action begins with validating the syntax of
          the Extended Communities attributes attached to FS NLRI in UPDATE
          packet.  Since FSv1 and FSv2 operate on different NLRIs (AFI/SAFI
          sets), a single FS-EC action can apply to both FSv1 and FSv2 filters.
          If the FS-EC is not syntactically correct, the FS-EC community causes
          NLRI and FS-EC to be treated as withdrawal.</t>

          <t>If the FS-EC is syntacically correct, then the FS-EC check to
          determine if this node can perform this action. If not, the FS-EC is
          stored for transmittal to other nodes, but cannot be used in this
          node.</t>

          <t>If multiple syntactically correct actions that can be performed on
          are linked to the filtering rules defined in the NLRI in UPDATE
          packet, then the list of multiple actions are check for conflicts
          within a category. If conflicts exist within a multiple action set
          attached to a FSv2 filter, then the default case is to ignore the
          action set for installation in the node.  Optionally, if the ACO
          FS-EC may indicate if the BGP peer originating the FSv2 filter +
          action expects this "ignoring" of the action or specifical local
          configuration.</t>

          <t>An example of local configuration might be if rate limiting by
          byte and by packet are specified, the local configuration might allow
          both to be enacted in the hardware.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Failure of FS-EC action when processing a filter flow">
          <t>If one action in the ordered list fails for a traffic flow, the
          local node may be able to halt processing of the for. For example, if
          a DSCP value set and forwarding to VPN is specified AND the DSCP
          fails, the forwarding logic may allow the forwarding to the VPN to
          not occur.</t>

          <t>FSv1-EC current control the failure action by configuration and/or
          implementation defaults.</t>

          <t>The optional ACO FSv2-EC can inform the BGP receiving the FSv2
          information how the originator expects failures within the multiple
          actions in an action set will occur.  The ACO FSv2-EC is optional.</t>

          <t>FSv2 Implementations MAY wish to log the action failures
          encountered by FS actions (FSv1 or FSv2).</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="error-handling-and-validation" title="Error handling and Validation">
          <t>The following two error handling rules must be followed by all BGP
          speakers which support FSv2:

            <list style="symbols">
              <t>FSv2 NLRI having TLVs which do not have the correct lengths or
              syntax must be considered MALFORMED, and "treated-as-withdrawl".</t>

              <t>FSv2 NLRIs having TLVs which do not follow the above ordering
              rules described in section 4.1 MUST be considered as MALFORMED by
              a BGP FSv2 propagator, and treated "treated-as-withdrawl".</t>
            </list>

          The above two rules prevent any ambiguity that arises from the
          multiple copies of the same NLRI from multiple BGP FSv2 propagators.</t>

          <t>A BGP implementation SHOULD treat such malformed NLRIs as ‘session
          reset’ <xref target="RFC7606"></xref></t>

          <t>An implementation for a BGP speaker supporting both FSv1 and FSv2
          MUST support the error handling for both FSv1 and FSv2.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section title="Ordering of FS filters for BGP Peers which support FSv1 and FSv2">
        <t> FSv2 allows the user to order flow specification rules and the
        actions associated with a rule. Each FSv2 rule has one or more match
        conditions and one or more actions associated with each rule.</t>

        <t>FSv1 and FSv2 filters are sent as different AFI/SAFI pairs so FSv1
        and FSv2 operate as ships-in-the-night.  Some BGP peers in an AS may
        support both FSv1 and FSv2.  Other BGP peers may support FSv1 or FSv2.
        Some BGP will not support FSv1 or FSV2.  A coherent flow specification
        technology must have consistent best practices for ordering the FSv1
        and FSv2 filter rules.</t>

        <t>One simple rule captures the best practice:  Order the FSv1 filters
        after the FSv2 filter by placing the FSv1 filters after the FSv2
        filters.</t>

        <t>To operationally make this work, all flow specification filters
        should be included the same data base with the FSv1 filters being
        assigned a user- defined order beyond the normal size of FSv2
        user-ordered values.  A few examples, may help to illustrate this best
        practice.</t>

        <t>Example 1: User ordered numbering - Suppose you might have 1,000
        rules for the FSv2 filters.  Assign all the FSv1 user defined rules to
        1,001 (or better yet 2,000).  The FSv1 rules will be ordered by the
        components and component values.</t>

        <t>Example 2: Storage of actions - All FSv1 actions are defined ordered
        actions in FSv2.  Translate your FSv1 actions into FSv2 ordered actions
        for storing in a common FSv1-FSv2 flow specification data base.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Scalability and Aspirations for FSv2">
      <t>Operational issues drive the deployment of BGP flow specification as a
      quick and scalable way to distribute filters.  The early operations
      accepted the fact validation of the distribution of filter needed to be
      done outside of the BGP distribution mechanism.  Other mechanisms
      (NETCONF/RESTCONF or PCEP) have reply-request protocols.</t>

      <t>These features within BGP have not changed. BGP still does not have an
      action-reply feature.</t>

      <t>NETCONF/RESTCONF latest enhancements provide action/response features
      which scale.  The combination of a quick distribution of filters via BGP
      and a long-term action in NETCONF/RESTCONF that ask for reporting of the
      installation of FSv2 filters may provide the best scalability.</t>

      <t>The combination of NETCONF/RESTCONF network management protocols and
      BGP focuses each protocol on the strengths of scalability.</t>

      <t>FSv2 will be deployed in webs of BGP peers which have some BGP peers
      passing FSv1, some BGP peers passing FSv2, some BGP peers passing FSv1
      and FSv2, and some BGP peers not passing any routes.</t>

      <t>The TLV encoding and deterministic behaviors of FSv2 will not
      deprecate the need for careful design of the distribution of flow
      specification filters in this mixed environment.  The needs of networks
      for flow specification are different depending on the network topology
      and the deployment technology for BGP peers sending flow specification.</t>

      <t>Suppose we have a centralized RR connected to DDoS processing sending
      out flow specification to a second tier of RR who distribute the
      information to targeted nodes. This type of distribution has one set of
      needs for FSv2 and the transition from FSv1 to FSv2.</t>

      <t>Suppose we have Data Center with a 3-tier backbone trying to
      distribute DDoS or other filters from the spine to combinational nodes,
      to the leaf BGP nodes.  The BGP peers may use RR or normal BGP
      distribution. This deployment has another set of needs for FSv2 and the
      transition from FSv1 to FSV2.</t>

      <t>Suppose we have a corporate network with a few AS sending DDoS filters
      using basic BGP from a variety of sites. Perhaps the corporate network
      will be satisfied with FSv1 for a long time.</t>

      <t>These examples are given to indicate that BGP FSv2, like so many BGP
      protocols, needs to be carefully tuned to aid the mitigation services
      within the network. This protocol suite starts the migration toward
      better tools using FSv2, but it does not end it.  With FSv2 TLVs and
      deterministic actions, new operational mechanisms can start to be
      understood and utilized.</t>

      <t>This FSv2 specification is merely the start of a revolution of work –
      not the end.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Optional Security Additions">
      <t>This section discusses the optional BGP Security additions for BGP-FS
      v2 relating ROA <xref target="RFC9582"></xref>.</t>

      <section title="BGP FSv2 with ROA">
        <t>BGP FSv2 can utilize ROAs in the validation. If BGP FSv2 is used
        with BGPSEC and ROA, the first thing is to validate the route within
        BGPSEC and second to utilize BGP ROA to validate the route origin.</t>

        <t> The BGP-FS peers using both ROA and BGP-FS validation determine
        that a BGP Flow specification is valid if and only if one of the
        following cases:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>If the BGP Flow Specification NLRI has a IPv4 or IPv6 address in
            destination address match filter and the following is true:

              <list style="symbols">
                <t>A BGP ROA has been received to validate the originator, and</t>

                <t>The route is the best-match unicast route for the
                destination prefix embedded in the match filter; or</t>
              </list>
            </t>

            <t>If a BGP ROA has not been received that matches the IPv4 or IPv6
            destination address in the destination filter, the match filter
            must abide by the <xref target="RFC8955"></xref> and
            <xref target="RFC8956"></xref> validation rules as follows:
              <list>
                <t>The originator match of the flow specification matches the
                originator of the best-match unicast route for the destination
                prefix filter embedded in the flow specification", and</t>

                <t>No more specific unicast routes exist when compared with the
                flow destination prefix that have been received from a
                different neighboring AS than the best-match unicast route,
                which has been determined in step A.</t>
              </list>
            </t>
          </list>
        The best match is defined to be the longest-match NLRI with the highest
        preference.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This section complies with <xref target="RFC7153"></xref>.</t>

      <section title="Flow Specification V2 SAFIs">
        <t> IANA is requested to assign two SAFI Values in the registry at
        https://www.iana.org/assignments/safi-namespace from the Standard Action
        Range as follows:
          <figure>
          <artwork>

         Table 7-1 SAFIs

         Value   Description      Reference
         -----   -------------    ---------------
          TBD1   BGP FSv2        [this document]
          TBD2   BGP FSv2 VPN    [this document]

          </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Generic Transitive Extended Community">
        <t>IANA is requested to assign a type value from the "Generic
        Transitive Extended Community Sub-Types" registry at
        https://www.iana.org/assignments/bgp-extended-communities/bgp-extended-communities.xhtml

          <figure>
          <artwork>
       Table 7-3 - Generic Transitive Extended Community

       Value   Description                Reference       Controller
       -----  --------------------------  ---------------  ----------
        TBD4  FSv2 Action Chain Ordering  [this document]  IETF
          </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="FSv2 IP Filters Component Types">
        <t>IANA is requested to create a new "BGP FSv2 IP Basic Component Types"
        registry and indicate [this draft] as a reference.  The following
        assignments in the FSv2 IP Basic Filters Component Types Registry shold be
        made.</t>

        <t>
          <dl spacing="compact">
	    <dt>Registry Name:</dt><dd>BGP FSv2 Component Types</dd>
            <dt>Reference:</dt><dd>[this document]</dd>
            <dt>Registration Procedures:</dt><dd>0x01-0x3FFF Standards Action, 0x4000-0xFFFF FCFS.</dd>
	  </dl>
	</t>

	<table align="left">
	  <name>BGP FSv2 IP Basic Component Types</name>
	  <thead>
	    <tr>
	      <th>Type</th>
	      <th>Definition</th>
	      <th>Reference</th>
	    </tr>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <tr><td>0</td><td>Reserved</td><td>This document</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>10</td><td>IP Destination Prefix</td><td>This document</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>20</td><td>IP Source Prefix</td><td>This document</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>30</td><td>IPv4 Protocol / IPv6 Upper Layer Protocol</td><td>This document</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>40</td><td>Port</td><td>This document</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>50</td><td>Destination Port</td><td>This document</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>60</td><td>Source Port</td><td>This document</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>70</td><td>ICMPv4 Type / ICMPv6 Type</td><td>This document</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>80</td><td>ICMPv4 Code / ICPv6 Code</td><td>This document</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>90</td><td>TCP Flags</td><td>This document</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>100</td><td>Packet Length</td><td>This document</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>110</td><td>DSCP</td><td>This document</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>120</td><td>Fragment</td><td>This document</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>130</td><td>Flow Label</td><td>This document</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>4095</td><td>Reserved</td><td>This document</td></tr>
	  </tbody>
	</table>
      </section>

      <section title="FSv2 Filter Component Types">
        <t>IANA is requested to create the a new registry for "Flow
        Specification v2 Filter Component Types".</t>

        <t>Registration Procedures: 0x01-0x3FFF Standards Action.</t>

	<table align="left">
	  <name>Flow Specification v2 Filter Component Types</name>
	  <thead>
	    <tr>
	      <th>Type</th>
	      <th>Description</th>
	      <th>Reference</th>
	    </tr>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <tr>
	      <td>0</td>
	      <td>Reserved</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>1-49</td>
	      <td>Unassigned</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>50</td>
	      <td>L2 Traffic Rules</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>51-99</td>
	      <td>Unassigned</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>100</td>
	      <td>MPLS traffic rules</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>101-149</td>
	      <td>Unassigned</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>150</td>
	      <td>SFC Traffic rules</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>151-199</td>
	      <td>Unassigned</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>200</td>
	      <td>Tunnel Traffic rules</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>201-255</td>
	      <td>Unassigned</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>256</td>
	      <td>IP traffic rules</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>257-279</td>
	      <td>Unassigned</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>280</td>
	      <td>Extended IP Rules</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>281-24575</td>
	      <td>Unassigned</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>24576-32767</td>
	      <td>Vendor specific</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>32768-65535</td>
	      <td>Reserved</td>
	      <td>[this document]</td>
	    </tr>
	  </tbody>
	</table>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The use of ROA improves on <xref target="RFC8955"></xref> by checking
      to see of the route origination. This check can improve the validation
      sequence for a multiple-AS environment.</t>

      <t>>The use of BGPSEC  <xref target="RFC8205"></xref> to secure the
      packet can increase security of BGP flow specification information sent
      in the packet.</t>

      <t>The use of the reduced validation within an AS
      <xref target="RFC9117"></xref> can provide adequate validation for
      distribution of flow specification within a single autonomous system for
      prevention of DDoS.</t>

      <t>Distribution of flow filters may provide insight into traffic being
      sent within an AS, but this information should be composite information
      that does not reveal the traffic patterns of individuals.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-interfaceset" to="interface-set"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-redirect-ip" to="redirect-ip"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-path-redirect" to="path-redirect"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.hares-idr-fsv2-more-ip-actions" to="fsv2-more-ip-actions"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.hares-idr-fsv2-more-ip-actions" to="fsv2-more-ip-filters"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-v2" to="fsv2"/>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.0768"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.0791"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.0792"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.0793"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.1997"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2474"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4303"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4360"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4443"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4456"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4760"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5065"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5701"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7153"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7606"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7665"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8200"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8955"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8956"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9015"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9117"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9582"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-l2vpn"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-nvo3"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-srv6"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-interfaceset"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-redirect-ip"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-path-redirect"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-wide-bgp-communities"/>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6241"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8040"/>
      <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8205"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-v2"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.hares-idr-fsv2-more-ip-actions"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.hares-idr-fsv2-more-ip-filters"/>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
